<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Life &amp; death offered to the choice of the sons and daughters of Adam, or, A doctrinal essay towards the discovery of the broad way that leadeth to destruction, and also the narrow path that leadeth unto life being the substance of several sermons preach'd on Matth. 7, 13, 14 : in the entrance of which discourse you have something spoken occasionally touching judging of others, and also touching the giving of holy things to dogs, and casting pearls before swine.</title>
            <author>Carter, R., 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5924</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13693685</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13693685</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Life &amp; death offered to the choice of the sons and daughters of Adam, or, A doctrinal essay towards the discovery of the broad way that leadeth to destruction, and also the narrow path that leadeth unto life being the substance of several sermons preach'd on Matth. 7, 13, 14 : in the entrance of which discourse you have something spoken occasionally touching judging of others, and also touching the giving of holy things to dogs, and casting pearls before swine.</title>
                  <author>Carter, R., 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 53 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: R. Carter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VII, 13-14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101421:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIFE &amp; DEATH Offered to the choice of the Sons and Daughters OF ADAM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A Doctrinal Eſſay towards the diſcovery of the broad way that leadeth to Deſtruction, and alſo the narrow path that leadeth unto LIFE.</p>
            <p>Being the Subſtance of ſeveral SERMONS Preach'd on MATTH. 7. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>In the entrance of which Diſcourſe you have ſomething ſpoken occaſionally touching judging of others, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo touching the giving of holy things to dogs, and caſting Pearls before Swine.</p>
            <q>I call Heaven and Earth to record this day againſt you, that I have ſet before you life and deach, bleſſing and curſing; therefore chooſe life, that both thou and thy ſeed may live,<bibl>Deut. 30. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101421:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101421:2"/>
            <head>To my Friends and Neighbours in the Pariſh of <hi>Upton cum Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veii,</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all thoſe of adjacent parts that did uſe to attend upon my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in that place.</head>
            <head>The Spirit of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with Grace and Peace, be multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends and Neighbours,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the good will and pleaſure of God to grant me this mercy to be born in a time of great Light, and in a Land of Viſions, when, and where the Gospel was preach'd in great Power and Glory; and to encline my heart in the morning of mine age, to an attendance upon the preaching of the Goſpel, by thoſe whom he had eminently gifted and ſpirited for that Work; yea, to take hold of my heart by his Word, and ſo to engage me in the
<pb facs="tcp:101421:3"/> ſtudy of his will revealed in his word, that I could not ſettle my ſelf upon any ſecular employment, ſave onely, that while I did live at home, my dear Mother being a Widow, I was (as became me) ſerviceable unto her in that Calling God had ſet her in. In which time I had the happineſs of enjoying Communion with many of the Lords people, by which Communion I was furthered in the knowledge and underſtanding of Scripture.</p>
            <p>After this the Lord brought me into acquaintance and favour with ſeveral godly and able Miniſters, who (after ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of me) did tell me, that they did verily believe God had ſome work for me to do in the Miniſtry, and that God would find me out, and give me a clear call thereunto; which perſwaſion of theirs, anſwering the inclination that God had wrought in my heart almoſt from my Cradle, did the more unſettle me as to any worldly employment. And ſo it was, that about the 21. year of mine age I had ſeveral proffers as to publike Work, but ſtill there was ſomething or other did impede and hinder. In fine, being in the Countrey near <hi>Windſor,</hi> for my health's ſake, about <hi>May,</hi> 1654. I was deſired to preach amongſt you at <hi>Upton,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I did on the 27. of that inſtant.</p>
            <p>And after I had preach'd with you (you being deſtitute of a Miniſter) I was deſired to take hold of that opportunity for the doing of God ſervice; which deſire I did freely cloſe withall, and in order thereunto, after that I had obtained power from the then Supream Magiſtrate, I took poſſeſſion of the Pulpit to preach in, and the Houſe to dwell in.</p>
            <p>In this my undertaking I had but little external encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there being not much either of Maintenance or Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to be expected from you: As for Maintenance, its known to be very ſhort; and as for Love and Countenance, I could look for little, being at the firſt deſired but by a very few in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; and beſides, for that you did ſeem generally to expect thoſe things from him who ſhould be your Miniſter, which (unleſs I ſhould have ſinn'd againſt my Light and Conſcience) I could not do. I hope I am able to ſay in ſome good meaſure of ſincerity and truth, That my great ends were the glory of God, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:101421:3"/> of your precious ſouls. For I conſidering how you had been ſupplyed for ſixty years, or more (according to your own confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to wit, with a prophane Miniſtry; and alſo, that the means was ſo ſhort, that few good men (they being bound by the Law of God and Nature to provide for their Families) could accept of it; I did judge I might be of more ſervice among you then elſewhere. My Lord Chriſt had told me by his bleſſed Word, that in this Work I muſt not looke to meet with the great things of this world, as Riches, Honours, Friends, &amp;c. but on the contrary, to meet with Diſgrace, Contempt, Scorn, and Perſecution. And indeed, there was no reaſon for me to have expected other among you, but the ſetting of you in a flame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me; ſo that I might have walked by your doors in fear, have lai'n down, and roſe up in fear; have preacht in fear; My great Work in the Miniſtry being to pull down your ſtrong holds, to plunder you of that which is more dear to you than your Gold and Silver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> namely, your ſins, to take your Beloveds out of your boſome, to pull out your right eyes, and cut off your right hands; to take away your Gods from you, your Carnality, Hypocriſie, Superſtition, &amp;c. But it was otherwiſe ordered by the holy and wiſe God; for in the room of this I had your attendance upon my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and approbation of it, many of you confeſſing that the Word came in power upon you, convincing you of many things. I alſo received great reſpects and love from many. Nay more, after that I had been near two years among you, and you fully knew what I refuſed to do, (I being alwayes open-hearted among you as to the matters of my God) you did notwithſtanding (hearing of ſome Overtures made to me about a remove) deſire my continuance with you, and did manifeſt this deſire by ſubſcribing your Names to what you were freely willing to give me Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly for the ſupplies of my Family: Which Subſcription of yours, though it did not much augment my Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, yet it was to me ſo high an expreſſion of your love, and ſo clear a diſcovery of ſome Work that my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
<pb facs="tcp:101421:4"/> had wrought among you, that I reſolved thereupon to continue a longer time with you; and manifeſted this my reſolution to be real, by laying out a conſiderable ſum of money upon the Vicaridge-Houſe for my own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ommo lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And ſo through the good hand of God did cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nue with you until <hi>December, 1660.</hi> for which opportunity of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I do think my ſelf obliged for ever to bleſs the Lord that he ſhould call out ſuch a poor worm, and give him ſix years time to bear a publike Teſtimony for Chriſt in his generation.</p>
            <p>Now as for my departure from you, though the cauſe thereof be known to many of you, yet for the honour of the Goſpel, and clearing of mine own innocency, I ſhall give you a brief account thereof in this place.</p>
            <p>The greateſt Conteſt I had all along with many of you, was about the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and Burial of the Dead, you requiring of me that I would bury the Dead according to former cuſtome, and adminiſter the Seals in a promiſcuous manner to all in the Pariſh: The great Argument you preſt upon me was this, That theſe were Church-Duties, and ſo incumbent upon me as your Miniſter. Unto the which my general Anſwer was, That I could not underſtand that the Lord Christ (our great Arch-Biſhop) had laid any injunction upon his Ministers about the Burial of the Dead, and therefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the Obſervation of any Ceremony at Burials, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accompany the Corps to the Grave, and after a decent interment, to preach the Gospel to the Living when it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, or I thought my Labours would be accepted. But then for Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, I did readily grant them to be Church-Ordinances, and being ſuch (as I have often told you) did pre-ſuppoſe a Church-state, a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Goſpel-Diſcipline: Now this Goſpel-Diſcipline I found you not onely ignorant of, but very averſe unto, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to put the Neck into Chriſts Yoke: And theſe being Chriſts matters, and I but a ſteward, I durſt not do any
<pb facs="tcp:101421:4"/> thing therein without my Lords Commiſſion; and (according to my light) did not ſee how you could be in a capacity to receive, or I to adminiſter, without a ſubmiſſion to the Rules of the Gospel. Now though the violence of ſome in theſe matters was abated, (I judge through the power of the Word) yet there did remain much prejudice in the hearts of others againſt me, upon the account of my faithfulneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Lord and Maſter; which I did in a good meaſure d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcern, and have ſometimes told you, that that enmity and prejudice againſt Chriſt and his faithful Servants, that lay hid under the Garb of Courteſie and Civili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, when ever opportunity did afford it ſelf (if ſuch hearts were not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued) would break forth, and diſcover its ſelf according to its utmoſt ability. But notwithſtanding the prejudice of ſeveral, I did nevertheleſs abide with you till there was not above ſeven or eight dayes left by that Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, entituled, <hi>An Act for confirming and reſtoring Miniſters;</hi> Dated <hi>September 13. 1660.</hi>) to the Juſtices, to hear and determine ſuch Caſes: For that Act did expire on the 25th. of <hi>December</hi> next enſuing, and it was the 18th. of that inſtant before I received any Warrant to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before them upon that account, and then in the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that day was a Warrant brought to me, ſigned with the hands of two Commiſſioners. In the which Warrant there was nothing mentioned of complaint againſt me, but onely that as I expected any benefit by the Act for Confirmation of Miniſters, I ſhould appear before them and other Juſtices of the Peace, the next morning about ten of the Clock, at the Crown in <hi>Beconsfield.</hi> And in obedience to this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, I appeared; and when I came there, I found four of my Pariſhioners ready to appear againſt me; whom when there was five Juſtices come, (which made a Quorum) were called in unto them, &amp; the door ſhut. Theſe four perſons were ſworn, and upon their Oaths did ſay (among other things) that I had refuſed to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize my Pariſhioners Children (which was a truth upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned account) and not onely ſo, but that I had declared my
<pb facs="tcp:101421:5"/> judgement againſt Infant-Baptiſm. This they ſwore, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I had often declared for Infant-Baptiſm publikely; and beſides, the chief of thoſe that ſwore againſt me, his Wife was preſent at my Houſe when one of my own Children was baptized. And 2dly, They ſwore that I had refuſed to adminiſter the Lords Supper to the Pariſhioners (which was a truth <hi>ut ſupra</hi>) and not onely ſo, but that I had publikely preacht againſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>This they ſwore, notwithſtanding I had the Summer before, upon <hi>1 Cor. 11.</hi> preacht divers Sermons touching the Author, Nature, Excellency &amp;c. of that Ordinance.</p>
            <p>When theſe my Pariſhioners had done ſwearing, I was called in, and the Depoſitions ſworn againſt me, read. And when I heard what was ſworn againſt me, and withall did perceive their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, I told them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That as to my preaching againſt theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, it was known to be notoriouſly falſe, for that I did both in judgement and practice own them; but in that they ſaid <hi>I</hi> had not adminiſtred them to the Pariſhioners, they ſpake truth; for <hi>I</hi> had not, nor could not adminiſter theſe Ordinances to a people that would not ſubmit to Goſpel-Diſcipline. After <hi>I</hi> had thus ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they required me to withdraw; and after a little ſpace of time, called me in again, and read an Order unto me for my lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the poſſeſſion of the Vicaridge Houſe at <hi>Upton,</hi> at, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the 25. of the ſaid <hi>December.</hi> To the which <hi>I</hi> anſwered, that ſince it was the good pleaſure of my God that ſo it ſhould be, <hi>I</hi> was even glad <hi>I</hi> had a <hi>quietus eſt</hi> to my Conſcience, and a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from further trouble in that place. As touching this Order, <hi>I</hi> cannot but declare my judgement to be this, That doubtleſs it had been a moſt righteous Sentence againſt me, had that which my Neighbours ſwore been truth; for I do verily judge, that thoſe Miniſters that ſhall either corrupt the Ordinances of Chriſt with their own inventions, or elſe deny them, and preach againſt them, do both a like deſerve to be deprived of publike opportunities for preaching, and to have the Church-doors ſhut againſt them. <hi>I</hi> had now left me but one Lords day wherein <hi>I</hi> could preach Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively among you, at which time <hi>I</hi> preacht the ſubſtance of what follows in this ſmall Treatiſe. This Lords Day in the afternoon
<pb facs="tcp:101421:5"/> Providence ſo ordered it, that the four perſons that ſwore againſt me, were a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l preſent, which <hi>I</hi> judge they hardly ever were at one time all the ſix years <hi>I</hi> was amongſt you. At which time <hi>I</hi> took my farwel of you, and gave you a publike account of what was ſworn againſt me, in their hearing; and when theſe perſons came out of the place (as <hi>I</hi> was informed by ſeveral) they denied that they had ſo ſworn againſt me, notwithſtanding their Names, and what they ſwore, was ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſt in the Order drawn up for my ejectment. Which Order r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> after this manner, (as I am able to teſtifie, having a true Copy of the Order ſtill by me) <hi>Foraſmuch as it appeareth to the ſaid Commiſſioners</hi> (the Names of the Commiſſioners being aſſerted above the Order) <hi>upon the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of——that</hi> R. C. <hi>who pretends himſelf to be Vicar of</hi> Upton, <hi>in the County of</hi> Bucks, <hi>for many years</hi>
               <note place="margin">I mention no more of the Order, bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe theſe were the moſt material things in it.</note> 
               <hi>laſt paſt, refuſed, and ſtill doth refuſe to baptize Children, and hath declared himſelf againſt Infant-Baptiſm; and that he hath for many years laſt paſt refuſed to adminiſter the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper to his ſaid Pariſhioners, and hath publikely preach't againſt the ſame,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we order ſo and ſo.</hi> The reaſon why I give this account, is not out of any prejudice I have to thoſe Neighbours that did ſo proſecute, and therefore I have purpoſely omitted the naming of them, though they did as evil againſt me, and my Wife &amp; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as they could; for though we had a hole to put our heads in, provided by the Father of Mercies, yet it clearly appeared that it had been all one to them whether we had or not. But yet <hi>I</hi> can appeal to God in this, that all the hurt <hi>I</hi> wiſh them is, that God would give them repentance unto life. But the great end of this account is, that the Gospel may not ſuffer reproach for my ſake.</p>
            <p>After that <hi>I</hi> was thus ordered to depart and the Church-doors ſhut againſt me by the Wardens, <hi>I</hi> did with what convenient speed I could, remove my Family, and leave the place, And now ſince my departure from you, looking back upon my converſation among you, <hi>I</hi> find matter both of Humiliation, and alſo of Peace and Conſolation: That which doth afford me matter of Humiliation, is the conſideration of the deadneſs of mine own heart, and the ſtraitneſs of mine own ſpirit while with you, that <hi>I</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no more
<pb facs="tcp:101421:6"/> abundant in labours, no more in praying, in preaching publikely, and from houſe to houſe; that <hi>I</hi> did no more earneſtly and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately endeavour your converſion to Chriſt; though <hi>I</hi> have as much to plead as ſome others, <hi>viz.</hi> a weak and frail body, and other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions which the wants of my Family did adminiſter to me; yet <hi>I</hi> muſt acknowledge, that theſe things do afford me matter of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, to conſider that God ſhould give me ſo large an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and that my heart ſhould not (as it ought) be enlarged in the work of my God. But then on the other hand, there are ſome things do afford me matter of peace and comfort, as, 1. In that <hi>I</hi> was (by the power of God) kept faithful to my light, with reference unto Goſpel-Adminiſtrations; <hi>I</hi> would not for all the world that <hi>I</hi> had come over to you in the adminiſtration of the Lord's Supper, and Baptiſm, in a promiſcuous way. 2. In that <hi>I</hi> did deſign and endeavour (as <hi>I</hi> could) the obtaining of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and went as far as <hi>I</hi> did judge the ſhooes of the Goſpel would carry me, to accompliſh this my deſign. 3. In that <hi>I</hi> did continue with you ſo long as <hi>I</hi> could; had <hi>I</hi> come away ſooner, <hi>I</hi> might have broken my peace; and had <hi>I</hi> continued longer, <hi>I</hi> might have undone my Family, and done you no good, being deprived of opportunity to preach the Goſpel, amongſt you. 4. In that <hi>I</hi> am not without hopes that God did by my Miniſtry work upon ſome of your ſouls; <hi>I</hi> am ſure as to conviction there was work done. Now that work may be done, where there's none, and carryed on where there are any beginnings thereof, is the deſign of this Book, which <hi>I</hi> do heartily preſent unto you of the Pariſh, and alſo unto thoſe of adjacent parts, that did uſe to attend upon my Miniſtry, as a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that dear love and affection <hi>I</hi> bear to your ſouls, deſiring your acceptance in the Lord. Now to him that is able to ſubdue moſt rebellious ones, and to preſerve ſubdued and enlightened ones from falling, and to preſent them faultleſs before the preſence of his glory with exceeding joy; to him do <hi>I</hi> commend you all, deſiring that to this onely wiſe God our Saviour, you may be enabled to give (as is moſt due) all Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power, now and ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, to ſerve you in the Lord, R. CARTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:101421:6"/>
            <head>LIFE and DEATH OFFERED TO THE CHOICE OF THE Sons and Daughters OF ADAM.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Matth. 7. 13, 14.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>13. <hi>Enter ye in at the ſtrait Gate; for wide is the Gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be that go in thereat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>14, <hi>Becauſe ſtraight is the Gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are part of Chriſt's Sermon upon the Mount, which he preach'ts to his Diſciples, and not onely to them, but alſo to the multitude of people that did croud after him, as appears by the two laſt verſes of this Chapter:—<hi>When Jeſus had ended theſe ſayings, the</hi> [People] <hi>were aſtoniſhed at his Doctrine: for
<pb facs="tcp:101421:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e taught them as one having Authority, and not as the Scribes:</hi> Of which Sermon this Evangeliſt doth give us the largeſt account, taking up the 5, 6, and 7. chap. of this Goſpel. The ſubſtance of this Sermon is to diſcover what bleſſed ones are, and what what bleſſed ones ought to do.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What bleſſed ones are, chap. 5. 3, to the 13. <hi>viz.</hi> Poor<note place="margin">The pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>port of Chriſt's Sermon on the Mount.</note> in ſpirit, true mourners, meekned ones, ſuch as do hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs, merciful, pure in heart, peace-makers, though by the world they are accounted troublers, and ſowers of ſedition, and upon that account not fit to live; yet by Chriſt they are known and judged to be the children of peace. Now our Lord Jeſus whom God ſent into the World to bleſs his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple *, doth here declare the perſons thus qualified to be bleſſed<note place="margin">Acts 3. ult.</note> perſons: Though we are to take notice, that theſe qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not laid down as the cauſes of bleſſedneſs, (which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone the eternal love of God in Chriſt) but as the properties of ſuch as are ſo bleſſed.</p>
            <p>And then finally, our Lord Chriſt doth declare theſe bleſſed ones to be the objects of the wickeds hatred and envy; and that notwithſtanding they are ſo, yet he doth (for the comfort and eſtabliſhment of all his) declare the perſons ſo qualified as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note n="†" place="margin">Thoſe that are not ſo qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied, whatſoever, they may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the profeſsion of Religion, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are not bleſſed.</note>, to be never the leſs bleſſed and happy at preſent; and as for their future ſtate, it will be ſo much the more glorious, by how much the more of perſecution they have undergone in this world above others.</p>
            <p>The other part of this Sermon is to ſhew what bleſſed ones ought to do. And for this (in general) he teacheth, that they (being the Salt of the Earth) ſhould labour to ſeaſon others, walking in each part of their converſation ſo, as that wicked ungodly men <hi>ſeeing their good works, might glorifie their Father</hi>
               <note place="margin">* Matth. 5. 6</note> 
               <hi>which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before he deſcends into particulars, he doth endeavour to eſtabliſh his Diſciples in this perſwaſion, that he came not to deſtroy the Law, to derogate from the Divine Authority there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to cauſe any part of it to be judged falſe and unprofitable, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to releaſe his people from obedience to the Moral Law which he chiefly intends in this place, as appears by the following ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;)<note place="margin">Chriſt came to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Law.</note> but he came to fulfil it, that is, 1. To anſwer all thoſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101421:7"/> and repreſentations of him exhibited in the Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alſo to accompliſh whatſoever was foretold of him by the holy Prophets. <hi>2dly,</hi> To fulfil it, that is to give a perfect and compleat obedience to every tittle and Iota of the Law, in the ſtead and room of the poor condemned ſinner; which obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience being imputed to the ſoul (as it is to every true believer) the ſoul comes to have as legal a right to glory, as if he had fulfilled it in his own perſon. <hi>3dly,</hi> To fulfil it, that is, to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his people by his Grace and Spirit to obey God acceptably, doing that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, yea to fulfil the Law in deſire and affection, (for love is the fulfilling of the Law) though they cannot do it in an abſolute perfection in this life. A true Chriſtian (ſo far as he is ſanctified) in deſire and will doth keep the whole Law.</p>
            <p>Nay further, our Lord Chriſt is ſo far from giving them a diſcharge as to their obedience, that he telleth them, <hi>if their righteouſneſs did not exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>they could in no wiſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> *, could not be Members of the true Goſpel-Church here on earth, or ever enter into the fellowſhip of the Saints in that eternal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry above.</p>
            <p>Now by this more exceeding righteouſneſs, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in this place is meant none other then the inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of the Saints; that every one who will be the Diſciple, muſt in his obedience to God exceed the Scribes and Phariſees: And accordingly, the obedience of every true Chriſtian doth exceed theirs, and that in theſe two things, <hi>viz.</hi> Sincerity, and univerſality; theirs being (firſt) hypocritical, minding the outſide onely, and not regarding the heart; and then partial, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing zealous for ſome ſmall matters, and neglecting the more weighty matters of the Law.</p>
            <p>The Lord Chriſt having ſpoken thus in general, deſcends into particulars, and doth in the firſt place make a ſpiritual Expoſition of the ſeveral Precepts of the Moral Law, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of every Chriſtians ſerious conſideration, Chap. 5. 21. to the end.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>6th.</hi> Chapter he proceedeth to lay down ſeveral rules in ſeveral caſes, as firſt about giving of Alms: <hi>2dly,</hi> About
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101421:8"/> Prayer, under which head he condemns the practice of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,<note place="margin">We ſhould not make pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate prayers in a place of publike Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> who did love to pray ſtanding in the Synagogues, and in the corners of the ſtreets, that they might be ſeen of men. And notwithanding Chriſt doth here condemn this practice, &amp; require his people not to be like unto them, but contrariwiſe to make their private prayers in a private ſecret place: Yet how do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſuperſtitiouſly and wickedly follow their example, making their private peayers in the places of publike Worſhip. Perſons that it may be are wholly ſtrangers to private prayers at home, yet when they come to the place of publike Worſhip, after they have bowed towards the Eaſt, (where uſually the Altar ſtood) then down upon their knees to their private devotion; yea though it be in the time of publike Worſhip, when the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is either ſpeaking to God, or from God; I have often told you, that this praying for a bleſſing upon the Word preacht, ſhould be done at home in your Families and Cloſets, before you come to the publike.</p>
            <p>And then under this head, our Lord Chriſt doth alſo forbid vain repetitions, as if we thought that God would hear us for our much ſpeaking, and often repeating the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> He giveth rules about faſting: And <hi>4thly,</hi> about laying up of Treaſure in Heaven. <hi>5thly,</hi> About keeping the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (that leading faculty of the ſoul) clear and ſingle. And <hi>6thly,</hi> About the management of our affections as to the world, and all the concernments thereof. All this is contained in the ſixth Chapter.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>7th.</hi> Chap our Lord Chriſt doth firſt forbid raſh and unſcriptural judgement, wherewith we are apt to judge others:<note place="margin">Againſt raſh judgement.</note> Such a judging of others as hath nothing of love and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in it, but proceedeth from pride, malice, ſuſpition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not but that there is a Scripture-judgement to be made of<note place="margin">How we may judge others.</note> mens perſons and actions: We may judge ſuch as profeſs the Name of Chriſt, and walk according to the rule of his Word in the general courſe of their converſation, to be in a ſtate of grace: And though many of theſe prove hypocrites, yet we ſin not in our judgement, ſince we are to judge perſons by that which viſibly doth appear. It's true, God judgeth the life and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by the heart and inward principle; but we muſt judge the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101421:8"/> heart and inward principle, by the life and outward action. Thus <hi>Simon</hi> was judged, (<hi>Acts</hi> 8. 13. to the 25.) to have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and thereupon was baptized; and yet ſoon diſcovered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after ſuch a manner, as that <hi>Peter</hi> doth poſitively declare him for the preſent to be in the gall of bitterneſs, and bond of iniquity. According to this rule doth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> make his judgement of thoſe to whom he writes, to be Saints, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c. Rom 1. 7. 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 2. with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parallel Scriptures; whereby the Apoſtle doth not paſs an abſolute and final judgement of the bleſſedneſs of their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtate, but it is onely a judgement proceeding from cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, regulated by the Scripture.</p>
            <p>And then on the other hand, we may judge ſuch perſons as do live in a continual omiſſion of known and confeſſed duties, ſuch as hearing the Word preach't, prayer, reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that have nothing of God or his fear in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, neither mind it; we may judge ſuch to be in as wretched an eſtate as any Heathen in the World, ſuch Families being reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed among the Families of the Heathen, in that Prophetical prayer of <hi>Jeremiah, chap. 10. 25. Pour out thy fury upon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and upon the Families that call not upon thy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many ſuch Families are there in this poor Iſland, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that preaching and light that hath been of late years? People that do live like Heathens and Atheiſts, that eat their food like the Beaſts, not minding that God that ſpreads their Tables, and filleth their Cups for them, that in their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings down and riſings up, goings forth, and comings in, regard not the Lord, whoſe love and mercy it is that gave them a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that loadeth them with daily mercy: And yet how en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged even are ſuch perſons as theſe, if you deny unto them the Name of Chriſtians? Are not many of theſe ready to pull out the throat of their Miniſter, to ſuck his blood, or at leaſt to manifeſt a ſpirit of irreconcilable hatred and enmity againſt him, in caſe he ſhall deny to give forth the blood of Chriſt in the Supper, unto them, and deal by them as if they were the beſt Saints under Heaven?</p>
            <p>We may alſo judge perſons of a debauched life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that live wallowing in the very Cinques of ſin; as Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101421:9"/> Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be in the gall of bitterneſs, and bond of iniquity, to be in a ſtate of wrath and condemnation, <hi>John 3. ult.—He that believeth not—the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> Queſt. <hi>But how can we judge whether a man hath faith or no?</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſ. Jam.</hi> 2. A man is to ſhew his faith by his works. Mind this (as I have often told you) though there may be good works (as to viſible appearance) where there is no true Faith, yet where true Faith is, there the ſouls works, (I ſpeak as to the general courſe of the converſation) wil viſibly appear to be good, they cannot do otherwiſe; for if the tree be good, the fruit wil be good; ſo that though a hearing, praying perſon may be a hypocrite, yet a ſwearing, drunken, prophane, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous perſon cannot be a Chriſtian; the one may be a hypocrite, but the other can't be Chriſtian: Though I cannot ſay poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively of a viſibly holy perſon, That he ſhall go to Heaven; yet I may certainly ſay of a prophane man, That he ſhall go to Hell, if he dieth in that eſtate, without repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> Queſt. <hi>But doth it not ſavour of pride, for perſons to judge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be holy perſons, and good Chriſtians, and judge others to be outcaſts, and wicked perſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It's poſſible perſons may judge themſelves ſo, when <note>
                  <hi>Prov. 13. 12.</hi>
               </note> they are not ſo; judge themſelves to be <hi>pure, and yet not waſhed from their filthineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for any (notwithſtanding their delight in ſecret ſin, and the indulging curſed luſts) to judge themſelves more holy then others, this proceeds from pride and ſelf-love, and great blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: But now for perſons that are ſincere and upright towards God, to judge themſelves to be in the love and favour of God, looking upon God as their Father, and themſelves as his ſons and Daughters, and alſo judging others to be wicked, this is according to holy Scripture, 1 Joh. 5. 19, 20. <hi>And we know, that</hi> [We] <hi>are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickedneſs; And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given</hi> [Us] <hi>an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that we may know him that is true; and</hi> [We] <hi>are in him that is true, even in his Son, Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> Object. <hi>This was the judgement of an Apoſtle.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. None knoweth the heart but God: The Apoſtles
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101421:9"/> themſelves were not infallibile in their Judgements, if they had, <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer had not been baptized. They judged onely by what appeared to them; thoſe that appeared truly godly, they judged ſo; and thoſe that appeared otherwiſe, they judged otherwiſe. But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly, John</hi> ſpeaks here in the plural number, <hi>Us,</hi> and <hi>We;</hi> whereby is clearly intimated, that others as well as Apoſtles, may judge themſelves to be of God: Nay, he ſaith in the <hi>13th.</hi> ver. <hi>Theſe things have I written unto you, that ye may know that ye have eternal life;</hi> that ye may be able to try and examine your own ſtate, and make a judgement of your ſelves, whether you are the perſons that have a title to eternal glory, yea or no; and accordingly you ſhall find that he doth (for the furtherance of this work of ſelf-examination) in this Epiſtle characterize the Chriſtian by his doing of righteouſneſs, and loving the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>But further, this judgement is not onely lawful, but there is<note place="margin">Great reaſon for the paſsing of a Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> judgement. 1. Reaſ.</note> great ground and reaſon for it; As,</p>
            <p>1. If God's people ſhould not judge themſelves to be ſo, they would be guilty of very great ingratitude. We ought to be thankful for all mercies, but eſpecially for ſpiritual mercies. When God ſhal by a mighty hand have brought a ſoul out of the Devils Kingdom, into the Kingdom of his dear Son, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his love and mercy to it, what greater ſin can ſuch a ſoul be guilty of, then the not taking notice of the exceeding riches of Grace, ſo as to own it, and acknowledge it to the glory and praiſe of God? <hi>Col. 1. 12, 13. Giving thanks unto the Father, which hath made us meet to be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light, who hath delivered us from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of darkneſs, and hath tranſlated us into the Kingdom of his dear Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> From this ſprings all a Chriſtians comfort: Alas! what<note place="margin">2. Reaſ.</note> comfort can a Chriſtian have in this wicked, miſerable, reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, hateful world, were it not for this, [<hi>God is mine?</hi>] Pſal. 48. ult. <hi>For this God is our God for ever and ever, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 25. 9.—<hi>Lo, this is our God, we have waited for him, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 41. 10. <hi>Be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, for I am thy God, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 63. 16. <hi>Doubtleſs thou art our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Iſrael acknowledge us
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101421:10"/> not: Thou Lord art our Father, our Redeemer, thy Name is from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Wicked prophane men they do judge themſelves to be<note place="margin">3. Reaſ.</note> the people of God, and good Chriſtians, and thereupon do lay claim to the ſeals of the Covenant, Baptiſm and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and do judge holy and religious perſons to be a company of hypocrites, which are the worſt ſort of wicked perſons in the world, and ſhall undergo the greateſt torments in Hell: Then ſurely the true ſincere Chriſtian may judge God to be its Father, and Chriſt its Saviour; and on the contrary, judge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wicked men to be (as the Scripture declareth them to be) in a ſtate of wrath, <hi>without God in the world, and ſtrangers to the Covenant of promiſe,</hi> Eph 2. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> There are a ſeveral duties to be performed upon this<note place="margin">4. Reaſ.</note> Judgement; as thus, We are to do <hi>good to all, but eſpecially to them of the Houſhold of Faith:</hi> Now this cannot be done, except<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> we may judge ſome to be of the Houſhold of Faith. <hi>The wicked</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 27.</note> 
               <hi>is an abomination to the juſt:</hi> It follows thence, that the juſt doth know him, and judge him to be wicked.</p>
            <p>The wicked are to be withdrawn from, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. then they muſt be firſt diſcovered, known, and judged to be ſo, elſe we break the rule of Charity by withdrawing from them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they are perſons with whom we have formerly had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in ſpiritual matters; for from ſuch we ought not to withdraw without cauſe.</p>
            <p>By all which it appears, that notwithſtanding Chriſt doth here forbid raſh Judgement, yet it hinders not that a Stripture Judgement may be made. Nay our Lord Chriſt in this <hi>7th.</hi> ch. doth plainly declare his Will to be, that according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Judgement ſhould all his people walk.</p>
            <p>According to this Rule ſhould Hearers walk with reſpect to<note place="margin">Hearers may paſs a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture judgment on their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, yea ought to do it.</note> their Teachers, and alſo Teachers and Miniſters with reſpect to their people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, People with reſpect to their Teachers, <hi>ver. 15. Beware of falſe prophets which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly are ravening Wolves.</hi> But Lord (might the Diſciples have ſaid) How may we know them? Know them! (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>you may know them by their fruits,</hi> ver. 16. This generation of raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101421:10"/> Wolves and falſe prophets God doth generally ſuffer them (for the good of his people, leſt they be drawn away by them) by one means or other to diſcover themſelves by their fruits, either by ſuperſtitious and idolatrous practices, thruſting in their own inventions into the Worſhip of God, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all thoſe that will not conform even to the death, and that upon a pretence of zeal to the Churches peace (for that is their ſheeps cloathing they wear to hide their abominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) Or elſe by their debauchery and prophaneneſs, whereby they make it to appear as clear as the Sun at noon, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they may appear zealous for Church-Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and plead the holineſs of places, Orders, Canons, Garments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet that they are perfect enemies to a holy life, and to the power of Godlineſs, Deceivers and Hereticks when they plead the Kingly Office of Chriſt in his Church, and are holy in their lives, are of all perſons in the world moſt dangerous, and fitteſt to propagate the deſign of the Devil, who often appears as an Angel of Light, that he may deceive. For holineſs in a Leader or Teacher is of a very drawing, convincing Nature. When therefore any new notion is delivered to us, that is contrary to the ancient received faith of the Saints, the more glorious the pretence is under which it comes; the more ſhould we fear it, and the more carefully ſhould we ponder it in the ballance of the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>But now when God ſhall ſuffer deceivers by their prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and debauchery ſo to diſcover themſelves, as that he that runs may read of what kind of ſpirit they are, and whoſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt they are advancing; wo to thoſe that ſhall join with a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration thus diſcovered, a generation upon whom the marks of God's wrath and diſpleaſure are. He walks not by this rule that can be content to hear his Pariſh-Miniſter, though he be never ſo ſuperſtitious in his Worſhip, or prophane in his life.</p>
            <p>Alſo, according to this Rule ſhould Teachers walk with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their people, Ver. 6. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto dogs, neither caſt ye the Pearls before Swine, leſt they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rent you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein Chriſt doth declare it to be lawful to call dogs dogs, &amp; ſwine ſwine; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> cannot be meant of irrational creatures call'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101421:11"/> by thoſe Names, but of men and women of prophane and wicked lives. Now unto ſuch muſt not be caſt pearls, which may have reference unto private reproof and admonition.</p>
            <p>There is a great deal of Wiſdom to be uſed in giving private and particular reproof to prophane perſons; for that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Reprove not a ſcorner, leſt he hate thee. He that reproveth a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9 7. 8</note> 
               <hi>ſcoruer, getteth to himſelf ſhame; and he that reproveth a wicked man, getteth to himſelf a blot.</hi> There was a time when <hi>David</hi> was ſilent, becauſe the wicked were preſent. To admoniſh or reprove ſome wicked prophane wretches, eſpecially in ſome of their mad moods and fits, or at ſuch a time to be ſpeaking to them concerning the excellency of Chriſt, and concernments of Eternity, would be but to expoſe the Truths of Chriſt to great contempt and reproach, and to draw forth their curſed luſts and paſſions, giving them thereby opportunity to vent that inward hatred they have againſt Chriſt and all his concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Again, by holy things, and pearls, may be underſtood the ſacred and holy things of God's Houſe, ſuch as the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Lords Supper. Indeed the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel belongs to all; It's to be <hi>preach't to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
               <note place="margin">Great differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between preaching &amp; adminiſtring the Lords Supper.</note> (Mark 16. 15.) Dogs and Swine, to the vileſt ſinners in the world; and it's the duty of all that live within the ſound of the Goſpel, to attend upon it. But now the Lords Supper is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Ordinance, appointed and inſtituted to be practiſed by, and adminiſtred unto, not Dogs and Swine, but Sons &amp; Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: It's a wicked man's duty to hear the Word preacht, but not to come to the Lords Supper: Before he comes to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, he muſt look after repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; which Faith in Chriſt takes in not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the aſſent of the Judgement, but alſo the conſent of the will, not onely the knowing, but the loving and imbracing of truth, <hi>Heb. 11. 13—were perſwaded of the promiſes</hi> (there was the aſſent of the Judgement) <hi>and embraced them,</hi> there was the conſent of the will.</p>
            <p>It's the duty of a Miniſter by all means poſſible, to entice and draw the people, be they never ſo ignorant and prophane, to the hearing of the Word, but he greatly ſins if he perſwades, draws, much more if he ſhall compel an ignorant, prophane people to come to the Lord's Table.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101421:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Some Miniſters may here object and ſay, <hi>Though I do perſwade my people to come to the Lords Supper, yet I diſcharge my ſelf, I tell them how they ſhould be qualified, and the danger of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unprepared: And ſo I am clear from the gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt of their blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The Text ſaith, <hi>Give not holy things to dogs,</hi> How then canſt thou diſcharge thy ſelf, when notwithſtanding thou telleſt the people they ought to be ſo and ſo qualified, to have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, repentance, love to God and his people, &amp;c. and that if they come unprepared, they make themſelves guilty of the blood of Chriſt, and eat and drink to themſelves damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which are very aſtoniſhing conſiderations) and yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs doſt receive ſuch to this Ordinance as are known to be very ignorant, and alſo very diſſolute and prophane. And unto every one of theſe thou ſaiſt, delivering the bread, The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was given for [<hi>thee</hi>] take and eat this in remembrance that Chriſt dyed for [<hi>thee.</hi>] And deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Cup, The Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was ſhed for [<hi>thee;</hi>] drink this in remembrance that Chriſt's blood was ſhed for [<hi>thee.</hi>] It was Gods command to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> that he ſhould ſeperate the precious from the vile, (<hi>Jer.</hi> 15. 19.) But contrariwiſe, ſome men do ſeparate the vile from the precious, do by the vileneſs of their own lives, and the corruptneſſe of their communions, forcibly (as I may ſo ſpeak) keep off ſuch as do truly fear the Lord from joining with them, &amp; ſo become a ſeperated company of ignorant, prophane, vile perſons.</p>
            <p>Now whether in this practice thou canſt ſo clear thy ſelf, as not to be guilty of the blood of thoſe ſouls as ſhall be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened in a way of wickedneſs by their receiving the Lords Supper from thy hands, and ſtrengthened in their hope of Gods love, and eternal life (notwithſtanding a wicked courſe) for that thou doſt tell them in the adminiſtration of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that the Body of Chriſt was given for them, and his blood ſhed for them: I ſay, this thing is worthy of thy ſerious conſideration. That expreſſion of the Lord Chancellor in his ſpeech on the <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1661. is very ſignificant, and will be found undoubtedly true at the great day of Chriſt, &amp; might well (for the conſideration and caution of all the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi>) be written over every Communion Table, namely,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101421:12"/> 
               <hi>That to poiſon a man at the Lords Supper, would be worſe then to kill him in a Tavern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what is the reaſon that ſome men are ſo general<note place="margin">Why ſome Miniſters are ſo general in admiſsion to the Lords Supper,</note> in their admiſſion to the Lords Supper, and ready (not onely to invite all, but) even to compel them (had they power) to come, how unworthy ſoever they may be?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am not able to ſay why, except for ſuch reaſons as theſe, which I wiſh were not found too true, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe, that ſhould they make uſe but of the outworks of Diſcipline, it would reach themſelves as well as the people: For, if a Drunkard ſhould be kept out from receiving, then he deſerves to be kickt out, and not ſuffered to adminiſter: If a ſwearer be unworthy to receive, he is much more unworthy to adminiſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rom. 2. 3. <hi>Thinkeſt thou this, O man, that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt them which do ſuch things, and doſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the Judgement of God? Thou therefore which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, commit adultery, and doſt thou do the very ſame things?</hi> From the 17. to the 25.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>2dly,</hi> It's poſſible they may either want money, or love mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; ſo that the gain and profit that comes in by the multitude of Communicants, may be another reaſon. But</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>3dly,</hi> It may be there may dwell ſome in the pariſh that do truly fear God, or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eaſt lie under ſome convictions of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and theſe perſons having received light to the contrary, dare not ſit down in ſuch corrupt Communions. Now out of prejudice to theſe (there being an old enmity between the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed of the Serpent) the pariſh Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may not onely invite and perſwade all to come, but (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his power) force and compel them, or at the leaſt, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that if they come not, they ſhall be indicted, and ſo and ſo proſecuted; and all this to torment and afflict the beſt in the pariſh.</p>
            <p>Here we may conſider into what a <hi>dilemma</hi> ſuch Miniſters do bring their people, telling them on the one hand, that if they eat and drink unworthily, they eat and drink damnation to themſelves; and yet on the other hand do threaten, that if they come not to the Communion, they ſhall undergo ſuch and ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101421:12"/> penalties: So that now if a perſon doth judge himſelf unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, he muſt either venture his own damnation, or elſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing of what trouble and loſs the Miniſter can put him to: Oh horrible wickedneſs!</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Are there ſuch Miniſters in England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am not able to ſay there are not; but this I pray hear tily, that if ſuch there be, God would be pleaſed either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them, or elſe caſt them forth as dung in the midſt of the Land.</p>
            <p>It's poſſible ſome willing to juſtifie themſelves in this practiſe may thus reply, or at leaſt we wil ſuppoſe they do ſo: The reaſon or argument of this prohibition, not to give that which is holy to dogs, is, leſt they turn again and rent you: Now we fear not by what we do, the peoples rending of us; our diſcoveries of truth are not ſo piercing, but the people can bear them well enough; eſpecially ſince we do not trouble their Houſes or Chambers with them; We love not this preaching from Houſe to Houſe, perſwading men to purity, it tends to Sedition and Faction: And as for our reproofs of ſin, they are moſtly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; and we know how to reprove ſin in ſuch a ſuperficial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that it ſhall not offend any. Our people know we cannot preach, but we muſt ſometimes ſpeak againſt exorbitant practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but then if at ſometimes (to pleaſe ſome whimſey-headed perſons in our pariſhes) we happen to ſpeak more againſt ſin then ordinary, or then we can do freely, we are ſure, by our plauſible complying converſation; to make up that offence quickly with the honeſt Orthodox party in our pariſhes, that they ſhall not be offended with us, or the Church for it.</p>
            <p>And then as for the Lords Supper, general admiſſion is very pleaſing; it's more likely if we ſhould deny it, they would rend us, rend our tythes from us, yea our very lives, were it in their power. Our way therefore is, to pleaſe the people in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Seals, and to hold a free converſation with them, keeping up good fellowſhip among the elder ſort, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging the younger in their lawful recreation upon the Lords day, letting them alone with their <hi>May-Poles</hi> and <hi>Whitſun-Ales, &amp;c.</hi> And by this means we are perſwaded we gain more (ten to one) then the <hi>Puritans</hi> can in their preciſe way. This bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101421:13"/> duly conſidered, we judge our ſelves not much concerned in this prohibition, it being grounded upon the reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thou haſt ſpoken for thy ſelf as much as well thou canſt; and I do grant, that thou managing thy matters as thou haſt ſaid, there is no viſible cauſe of fear that thou ſhalt be rent by the prophane about thee, though (it may be) they may rend better men then thy ſelf a thouſand fold. But it will be thy wiſdom not to provoke theſe Dogs and Swine; for if thou ſhalt be too quick with them, and call them to ſay before they have had time to con their Leſſons, and then whip them becauſe they han't them perfect, they'l be ready to fall upon thee; and if they be but once provoked, they will out with all thy wickedneſs; they'l tell thee to thy face of thy Oaths, Drunkenneſs, Wantonneſs, &amp;c. And what will they then ſay? <hi>Thou a Miniſter! Thou a Devil.</hi> Thus will they ſpeake, though they themſelves be as vile as may be.</p>
            <p>But I would here mind thee of that which happily thou hadſt forgot; and that is, that there is a double argument uſed by Chriſt, why holy things ſhould not be given to dogs, <hi>&amp;c. 1. Leſt they trample them under their feet.</hi> And then <hi>2dly, Turn again, and rent you.</hi> Now thou haſt taken that concerns thy ſelf, but mindes not that which concerns the glory of God, and the honor of his Ordinances. Chriſt would have his people be prudent, and avoid rending if they may; but upon their lives they muſt take care of his glory and honor. So that when it comes once to this, that either they muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to rending, or the Ordinances of Chriſt to pollution and contempt, a Miniſter of the Goſpel ought (in ſuch a caſe) to chooſe his own rending.</p>
            <p>Thou oughteſt therefore to conſider, whether by inviting and entertaining vile perſons at the Lords Table, thou doſt not expoſe his Ordinance to very great contempt; whether perſons will not greatly undervalue it, ſince they can have it upon ſuch terms; and alſo thou ſhouldſt conſider whether by thy free converſation among thy people, thou doſt not ſtrengthen them in their wickedneſs, and (as it were) with a light in thy hand lead them to Hell.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101421:13"/>
            <p>I have been the larger here, becauſe uſually when we ſpeak againſt the admiſſion of ignorant prophane perſons to the Lord's Table, the reply preſently is, <hi>Judge not, leſt ye be judged;</hi> and ſo this Scripture comes to be abuſed, by being brought for that which Chriſt did not intend it.</p>
            <p>Another thing Chriſt ſpeaks unto in this <hi>7th.</hi> chap. is, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate prayer; 7, 8, 9, 10, 11: ver. And the laſt thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Text is that excellent Moral Precept, <hi>To do to others</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> 
               <hi>as we would be done unto.</hi> This Precept is taught by the very Light of Nature, and is writ in the heart of every man; it's a Rule known to all, talked of by moſt, and practiſed by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few.</p>
            <p>We ſhall now (God willing) ſpeake of the Text it ſelf: <hi>Enter ye in at the ſtrait Gate, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words ſeem to be ſpoken by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt<note place="margin">The Text o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</note> to prevent an objection or query that might have been here made; as thus might it have been objected, Lord, in caſe none are bleſſed but ſuch as be, and do as thou haſt ſaid; ſuch as be poor in ſpirit, pure in heart, &amp;c. and then ſuch as in their Converſations walk as Lights in the World, conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (at leaſt in deſire) to the moſt ſpiritual part of the Law; pulling out their right eyes, &amp; cutting off their right hands, denying themſelves in every thing, bleſſing them that curſe them, praying for them that perſecute them; making it their chief end to approve themſelves to God rather then to man in every duty; living by Faith as to all outward enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; not judging any, but according to Rule; condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no man for that which they allow in themſelves; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing earneſtly and importunately; doing to every man as they would be done unto: Then ſurely, Lord, thy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline is a very ſevere Diſcipline, and there are but very few that will be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Our Lord Chriſt doth in the Text reſolve that Query, and doth faithfully acknowledge his Diſcipline to be ſevere, and that the way to heaven is a <hi>ſtrait narrow way.</hi> The parallel Scripture to this (<hi>Luke</hi> 13, 2, 324.) we find brought in as a Reply to a Queſtion of this nature.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101421:14"/>
            <p>In theſe words you have two things conſiderable,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. You have ſomething plainly aſſerted by our Lord Chriſt as an undoubted truth; to wit, That the way to true happineſs is ſtreight and narrow, but the way to deſtruction broad and eaſie; and thereupon there is but few that do walk in the former, but moſt in the latter way.</item>
               <item>2. You have the Exhortation of our Lord Chriſt, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon this plain and undoubted Aſſertion, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſince the way to deſtruction is broad and full, we ſhould therefore beware of it; and ſince the way to glory is nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, we ſhould therefore <hi>enter in</hi> (ſaith this Scripture) <hi>ſtrive to enter in</hi> (ſaith Luke) <hi>at this ſtrait gate, and to walk in this nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>That which I ſhall ſpeak unto, will be the undoubted Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion in the Text; and as for the Exhortatory part, that will fall in by way of improvement.</p>
            <p>Two things are then to be ſpoken unto:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. (For that I ſhal ſpeak to firſt, though it be not firſt in<note place="margin">1 Doctr.</note> in the Text) <hi>That the way to hell and deſtruction, is a broad eaſie way, and the moſt walk in it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the way to heaven and bleſſedneſs, is a ſtrait narrow way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Doctr.</note> 
                  <hi>and few find it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the handling of the firſt particular, I ſhal propound, and reſolve three Queres.</p>
            <p>1. What is this broad way? 2. What is that deſtruction it leadeth unto? 3. How it cometh to paſs that (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it leadeth to deſtruction, yet) the moſt walk in it: Of theſe in their order.</p>
            <p>1. What is this broad Way?<note place="margin">What the broad way to deſtruction is.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By this way (in general) we may underſtand the way of the Unregenerate man. God made man a glorious creature, but by his Fall he corrupted himſelf, and begat his Children in his own corrupt and filthy likeneſs; ſo that all the generation of mankind are naturally under ſin <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> and out of the right way; by nature children of wrath <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 2.</note>, born with their faces towards Hell, and their backs upon God, and the concernments of his Kingdom; <hi>The whole world ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in wickedneſs</hi> (1 Joh. 5. 19.) <hi>All as ſheep going aſtray,</hi> 1 Pet.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101421:14"/> 2. 25. So that without a turn, without converſion there is no<note place="margin">Every unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon however qualified, is in the broad way to Hell. Five paths in the broad way</note> ſalvation, <hi>John</hi> 3. 3. But I ſhall a little expatiate, deſcending into particulars.</p>
            <p>In this broad way we may conſider theſe five paths all very broad, and leading to deſtruction. 1. The path of <hi>Ignorance. 2dly,</hi> Of <hi>Prophaneneſs. 3dly,</hi> Of <hi>Diſobedience. 4hly,</hi> Of <hi>falſe Worſhip.</hi> And <hi>5thly,</hi> Of <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The path of Ignorance, the want of the knowledge of<note place="margin">1. The path of Ignorance.</note> the true God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt; in whoſe face the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious attributes of God doth ſhine forth moſt clearly. Now the want of this, doth render the ſoul in a loſt and miſerable ſtate. 2 <hi>Cor. 4. 3. If our Goſpel be hid, it's hid to them that are loſt.</hi> Mind <hi>Hoſ. 4 6 John 17. 3. Rom. 10. 14. Without this knowledge the mind can't be good, Prov.</hi> 19. 2. A perſon may as well ſay he hath a good eye, though a blind one, as a good heart, though igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: There can be no truly good meanings, breathings, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirings, in the heart without light.</p>
            <p>Now in this blind dark path, doth all men naturally walk, <hi>Pſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 42. 6, 7. &amp; 49. 6 Mac. 4. 16.</note> 14. 2. <hi>Eph. 4. 18. Eph.</hi> 5. 8. And therefore Chriſt is given to <hi>be a Light to them that ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man underſtandeth not the things of God, neither can he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned;</hi> and becauſe <hi>he knoweth them not, therefore he cannot receive them, John 14. 17. 1 Cor. 2. ch.</hi> Seek therefore after the knowledge of God in Chriſt, and for the Lord's ſake take heed of adding to natural blindneſs, blindneſs of mind, and a hatred of the Light; for this obſtinate blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth more and more alienate the heart from God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 18. and bring condemnation with a witneſs, <hi>John 3. 19. This is the condemnation, that Light is come into the world, and men loved darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds were evil.</hi> Take heed of oppoſing, neglecting, refuſing, and deſpiſing the precious Goſpel, the means whereby you are to come to the knowledg of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The path of Prophaneneſs. This is the filthy, dirty<note place="margin">2. The path of Prophaneneſs.</note> path of a debauched, wretched life; the pollution of the world, the Cinque of ſin, when perſons ſhall live in all manner of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable wickedneſs, ſuch as ſwearing, drunkenneſs, unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, idolatry, Sabbath-breaking, witchcraft, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101421:15"/> path leads to deſtruction, is clear from theſe Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor. 6. 9, 10. Gal. 5. 19, 20. 21. Rev. 21 8. ult.</hi> &amp; 22. 15.</p>
            <p>That this path is broad and full, Experience doth teach if we look no further then our own Iſland, how doth Prophaneneſs and Debauchery ſpread it ſelf? How is the Lords Day propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, his Name blaſphemed, Holineſs deſpiſed, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> Becauſe of curſing, and ſwearing, and damning, the Land doth mourn, or rather ought to mourn. Do we not wiſh the Pox, and Plague of God upon each other daily, as if we would provoke the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to ſhoot his Arrows amongſt us? Is not the iniquity of <hi>Sodom</hi> to be found amongſt us. <hi>Pride, fulneſs of Bread, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of idleneſs, Ezek.</hi> 16. 49. And exceedingly aggravated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that of <hi>Sodom,</hi> in that it hath been againſt ſo many War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ſo much Light, and the exerciſe of ſuch love and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with us. Nay, may we not ſay concerning <hi>England,</hi> as of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> of old, <hi>(Hoſea 4. 2.) That by ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and committing adultery, they break out, and blood toucheth blood.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> There is the path of Diſobedience. It's true, the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> The path of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> perſon is diſobedient, foraſmuch as it's the duty of all to labour after the knowledge of God, and the debauched per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is a diſobedient perſon; but here I underſtand the Negative Chriſtian (if we may call him a Chriſtian) that pleaſeth himſelf that he is not ſo and ſo; no Swearer, no Drunkard, &amp;c. And foraſmuch as he cannot be charged with the commiſſion of groſs ſins, he judgeth his ſtate good. Now this is a path that doth moſt certainly lead to everlaſting ruine, and that becauſe the Goſpel doth require poſitive obedience. It's not what thou art not, or what thou haſt not done; but what thou art, and what thou haſt done, that will comfort thee upon a dying bed, and before a Judgement-ſeat. Thou ſaiſt thou haſt not walked<note place="margin">The Goſpel requireth po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo and ſo; Well, but haſt thou believed, repented, and obeyed the Goſpel? Theſe things are poſitively required. As firſt, the Goſpel requires Faith (which is a coming out of our ſelves to Chriſt for ſalvation, and a receiving of Chriſt upon Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terms,<note place="margin">A definition of Faith.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> as a King to rule, a Prophet to teach, and a Prieſt to ſave) 1 <hi>John 3. 23. Matth.</hi> 11. 28. And without this, no ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Luke 19. 27. John</hi> 3. 18.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101421:15"/>
            <p>Again, the Goſpel requireth repentance, <hi>Mat. 4. 17. Acts</hi> 2. 38. &amp; 3. 19. The Law knoweth no repentance, the Language thereof is, <hi>The ſoul that ſins muſt dye.</hi> Repentance unto life is a<note place="margin">A deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> pure Goſpel-Cammand, and comes in upon the account of the New-Covenant. Now that Repentance which the Goſpel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, it conſiſts, (firſt) In a ſence of ſin original and actual. Secondly, Humiliation for it. Thirdly, A hatred of all of that kind. Fourthly, a departing from it. And this Repentance is ſo required in the Goſpel that without it there is no ſalvation, Luke 13. 3. Pſal. 68. 21. <hi>God ſhall wound—the hairy ſcalp of ſuch an one as goeth on ſtill in his trespaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the Goſpel requires obedience, <hi>Matth. 20. 28. 1 Pet. 1. 15. 2 Cor. 10. 5. Rom.</hi> 6. 13. And this is ſo required alſo, that without it there is no entring into Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14. &amp; 5. 9. &amp; 2 <hi>Theſ. 1. 8. In flaming fire taking vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this in the fear of the Lord all ye civil ones, that though your lives may not be ſo vile as others, yet if that be wanting which the Goſpel doth require, above-mentioned, then as ſure as thou haſt a being in this World at preſent, ſo ſure wilt thou have a being with the Devils in everlaſting flames, if free grace prevent-not. This path is doubtleſs a broad path, thouſands have travelled to Hell in this path, looking for no more then the negative part of Godlineſs. To proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> There is a path of falſe Worſhip. As there is a true<note place="margin">4. The path of falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> Worſhip required in the firſt and ſecond Pretepts of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law, ſo there is likewiſe a falſe Worſhip in the world, which upon your ſouls you muſt beware of. Now this falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may be reduced to one of theſe two heads, <hi>viz.</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or Will-Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Firſt for Idolatry. Idolatry is the Worſhip of Idol-gods; and<note place="margin">Idolatry what it is.</note> this Idolatry is either external or internal.</p>
            <p>Internal Idolatry is the placing of that fear, truſt, love, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Internal I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, what it is.</note> which is due to the true God, upon ſomething elſe. This is a breach of the firſt Commandment, wherein God doth forbid heart-Idolatry.</p>
            <p>God doth require a precedency and preheminency in our affections, <hi>Deut</hi> 6. 5. Now this heart-worſhip is called natural
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101421:16"/> worſhip, and that becauſe it depends upon the very nature of God, conſidering what a God he is; and is due from us by the very Law of Creation; being by that Law bound to love, fear, truſt, &amp;c. the true God above all others in heaven or earth. And curſed is that ſoul that with-holds from God the <hi>male of his flock;</hi> which is the heart heart.<note place="margin">Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 ult.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Here note, that every man naturally hath an Idol in his heart; ſomething which he prefers before God, and the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his pretious ſoul: ſo that we may conclude every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſon to be a Heart-Idolater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>External Idolatry,</hi> is either the worſhipping of any thing<note place="margin">External Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry what it is.</note> beſides the true GOD, as a God; or, Secondly, The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of the true God by Idols and Images. The former is a breach alſo of the firſt Command, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me;</hi> and is expreſly forbid in other<note place="margin">Exod. 20. 3.</note> Scriptures, as <hi>Exod. 34. 10. Deut.</hi> 6. 14. Nay, other falſe gods were not to be once named amongſt them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 13. and the very places of Worſhip were to be deſtroyed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 2, 3. In this worſhip is nothing to be expected but wrath and damnation, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 14, 15. &amp; 29. 26, 27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9 20. From which wrath their falſe gods cannot ſave them, <hi>Jer. 10. 8, 14 15. Hab</hi> 2. 18, 19.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, There is another way of Idolatry, which God alſo abhors; and that is, the pretending to worſhip the true God by Idols and Images. This kind of Idolatry is a breach of the ſecond Command, which forbids the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to our ſelves graven Images, or the bowing down to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 5.</note> them, and worſhipping of them, if made by others: And this was the ſin of Iſrael in the matter of the Calf. <hi>Aaron</hi> and the reſt were not ſo blind, as to think the Calf was God, but they intended the worſhip of the true God by the Calf, as appears <hi>Exod. 32. 5. Aaron</hi> proclaimed, to morrow is a ſeaſt to the Lord, not to the Calf: and yet if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the the <hi>8th</hi> verſ of that Chapter, as alſo <hi>Pſal. 106. 19, 20. Act.</hi> 7. 41. you'l find, God did account it all one as if they had terminated their worſhip in the Calf; foraſmuch as theſe Scriptures ſaith plainly, That they did <hi>worſhip the Calf, and offered ſacrifice to the Idol, and rejoiced in the works of their own hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101421:16"/>
            <p>It's therefore a vain plea of the Papiſts to ſay, they do not terminate their Worſhip in the Image or Picture, but worſhip the true God by it: though they uncover the head, bow the body, bend the knee to the Image, yet all this is not worſhiping the Image, but God by it. And thus do Altar-Worſhipers plead, they bow before the Altar, but not to it; they worſhip not the Altar, but God by it. But the moſt High God will be worſhiped in ſpirit and truth, and<note place="margin">The drawing a picture of God or Chriſt is abominable.</note> not by Pictures and Images. To make therefore a Picture of the Trinity is abominable Idolatry. Conſider theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Deut. 4. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. Iſa.</hi> 40. 18, 19, 20. &amp; 46. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. And as for Chriſt, though indeed as man he was pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yet becauſe of that near union that was between the two natures, the drawing a picture of him muſt needs be very ſinfull and wicked. Both theſe kindes of Idolatry are to be fled from, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 14. 1 John 5. ult.</hi> God did ſo abhor it, that he gave order that their Groves &amp; high Places ſhould be deſtroyed, <hi>Deut. 7. 5. Iſa. 30. 22. 2 Cor. 6. 16. Num.</hi> 33. 53. and accordingly you'l finde the good Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did. This is a path that leads certainly to ruine; Pſal 97. 7. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded be all they that ſerve graven Images, that boaſt themſelves of Idols: Worſhip him all ye gods.</hi> You may do well here to conſider that ſevere Law (<hi>Deut.</hi> 13.) againſt thoſe that ſhould ſecretly intice to Idolatry; the 6th <hi>verſe</hi> to the 12. the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of which Law was this, That <hi>if a mans own ſon, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wife, friend, &amp;c. ſhould entice him ſecretly to the Worſhip of a falſe God, that then that man ſhould not conceal it, but his hand ſhould be firſt upon him to kill him, ſtoning him with ſtones untill he died.</hi> And the end of this ſevere Law is expreſt to be, That <hi>Iſrael might hear, and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 11. Of Will-Worſhip. The difference between na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The other part of Falſe Worſhip, is Will-Worſhip, that Worſhip which is founded purely upon mans will.</p>
            <p>Note here, that though natural Worſhip is founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very nature of God, and due by the very Law of Creation, and ſo needed no inſtitution for it, yet the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Worſhip of God (of which the ſecond Command treats) is built upon the command of God: ſo that God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101421:17"/> will own no Worſhip to be his, but what he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Hence it is, that though natural Worſhip abides ever the ſame, yet inſtituted Worſhip hath been divers. Under the Old Teſtament in one form, and under the Goſpel in another. And as all the Ceremonies under the Law were lawfull onely upon the account of Gods command,; ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that which doth warrant Church-conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Diſcipline, Ordination of Officers, Adminiſtration of the Seals, &amp;c. is nothing elſe but the command of God. And therefore when God ſpeaketh (in <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 31. &amp; 19 5.) againſt the offering of their Sons and Daughters to <hi>Baal,</hi> he ſaith not, I forbad this (though he had forbad it once and again, as <hi>Levit</hi> 18. 21. &amp; 20. 2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 31. &amp; 18. 2.) but it never came into my heart to require it. By Will-Worſhip then I mean mens additions unto, or ſubſtractions from the Word of God, in the matter of inſtituted Worſhip. This is forbidden <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2. &amp; 12. 32. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 6.</p>
            <p>Now this way of Will-Worſhip muſt needs lead to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting<note place="margin">Wherein the evil of Will-Worſhip con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſteth.</note> deſtruction; For that</p>
            <p n="1">1. It's committing high Treaſon againſt the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. To clip the King's Coyn is Treaſon, but to put our own ſtamp upon it is high Treaſon: To diminiſh ought from God's Law is very abominable, but to make Laws of our own is much more abominable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's the ſetting up of the Will and Wiſedom of man in oppoſition to the Authority and Wiſedom of Chriſt. That whereas we are commanded to do that which is right in the ſight of the Lord (<hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 17, 18. &amp; 12. 25, 28. &amp; 13. 18. &amp; 28. 14.) this is doing that which is right in our own eyes, as if we were wiſer then the Lord. It's the Language of the heart of an Idolater, I'le not have this man to rule over me; if I do him any homage, it ſhall be according to my own will.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is in Scripture called <hi>the Worſhip of Devils, Lev. 17. 7. Deut. 32. 17. 1 Cor, 10. 20. Rev. 9. 20. Pſal 106. 36, 37. 2 Chron.</hi> 11. 15. and that becauſe it's not God but the Devil that is ſerved by ſuch Worſhippers. It's a Worſhip of the Devils in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting, and that he by all means poſſible endeavours to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101421:17"/> ſtrengthen and eſtabliſh. Now the Worſhip of the Devil muſt needs lead to ruine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Idolatry and Will. Worſhip is that which cauſeth the Jealouſie of God to break forth. We have this word <hi>Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> mentioned in no Command but the Second, which trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of inſtituted Worſhip, and ſeveral times it's uſed in Scripture in reference to Worſhip, as <hi>Exod. 34. 10. Deut.</hi> 6. 14, 15. &amp; 32. 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 58. If you ask what Jealouſie is, <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>It's the rage of a man,</hi> Prov. 6 34. So that (to ſpeak with holy reverence) pollution in matter of Worſhip is that which putteth the holy God into a rage and fury, maketh him very wroth, and Who is able to ſtand when once the Jealouſie of God breaks forth? Now by all this it appears, that Idolatry and Will-Worſhip leadeth to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And now that this way of falſe Worſhip is nevertheleſs a broad path, appears, if we ſhall conſider, that moſt part of the world is without the knowledge of the true God: Some worſhiping the Sun, Moon, and Stars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome, Men, like themſelves; and ſome four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed Beaſts, and Creeping things: For the proof of which, the Scriptures are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly full; <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 1, and ſo on. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115. 4. &amp; 135. 15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Rom. 1. 21, 22, 23. 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 20. And then in that part of the world which is called <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> there Antichriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the Temple of God, ſetting up his Poſt by Gods Poſt, and his Pillar by Gods Pillar. <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 9, 10, 11, 12. There it ſaith, that <hi>Whoſoever ſhall worſhip the Beaſt, or receive his Mark, &amp;c. ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, that is poured out without mixture, into the cup of his Indignation, &amp;c.</hi> And yet you ſhall finde (<hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 3, 8.) that <hi>upon the healing of the deadly wound of the Beaſt, all thoſe whoſe names are not written in the Lambs book of Life, ſhall wonder after the Beaſt, and worſhip him.</hi> Now for the Lords ſake, and for your ſouls ſake look to it, that neither by threats nor flatteries you are brought to walk in this accurſed path.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But will not the Command of a Chief Magiſtrate excuſe mee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Daniel</hi> and the three Children had the command of the King, and yet that would not prevail with them,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101421:18"/> either to neglect the Worſhip of the true God, or to worſhip<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> chapters 3, &amp; 6.</note> a falſe God.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But may I not keep my heart to God, though I do ſubmit externally to a falſe, ſuperſtitious Will-Worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No: It's impoſſible for thee to give thy heart to God, and thy body to an Idol. <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me, and he that gathereth not with me ſcattereth abroad,</hi> Math. 12. 30.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The 5th and laſt is the Path of <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> The way<note place="margin">5. The path of Hypocriſie.</note> of Hypocriſie, is when men and women ſhall pretend to the true Worſhip of God, and ſeem zealons for his glory, and yet in heart be enemies to Chriſt, and the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. A Hypocrite is one that hath a Saints name and a Devils nature; one that hates the practice of that he knows and commends to others, <hi>Ezek. 33. 33. Jerem.</hi> 1. to the 12. <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>This is a Path that leads to Hell; for, 1. All ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons performances are abominable to God, <hi>Iſa</hi> 1. 11. &amp; 66. 3. <hi>Zech. 7. 4, 5, 6. Mal.</hi> 1. 7, 8. 2. There are ſeveral dreadfull words written againſt him, <hi>Mal. 1. ult. Iſai. 33. 14. Job</hi> 8. 13. &amp; 20. 5. &amp; 27. 8. &amp; 15. 34. &amp; 13. 16. <hi>Math. 24. ult.</hi> And this is alſo a broad path, Iſai. 9. 17. <hi>Every one is a hypocrite, &amp;c.</hi> Math. 7. 22. <hi>Many ſhall ſay in that day, &amp;c. And I ſhall profeſs unto them I never knew you: Depart from mee ye workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> Nay, among the Virgin-Worſhipers, ſuch as have not been polluted by Antichriſt, there will be as many fooliſh as wiſe. Thus much in anſwer to the firſt Querie, <hi>viz.</hi> What this broad way is. The</p>
            <p>Second Query propounded was, <hi>What deſtruction that is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it is the broad way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eadeth unto.</note> 
               <hi>which this broad way leadeth unto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Deſtruction hath two parts; which I ſhall but name.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the preſence of the Lord (the chiefeſt good) An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 8, 9. In flaming fire, taking venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>once on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. This deſtruction will be to the company of the Divels
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101421:18"/> and damned Spirits, in everlaſting flames, under God's wrath, and the terrour of a gnawing Conſcience for ever and ever. <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25. 41, 46, 30. Mar. 44 46, 48</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Query to be reſolved is, <hi>How it comes to paſs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Why moſt walk in this broad way.</note> 
               <hi>that the moſt of men travel in this way which leadeth unto deſtruction?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the ſolution of this Query, I ſhall lay down theſe five Reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. Becauſe it's mans own way. Every man is born with <note>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> his face towards hell, as before ſaid, and thitherward doth he travel until converſion. Now, ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> Prov. 16. 2. <hi>The waies of a man</hi> (that is, the unregenerate man) <hi>are clean in his own eyes, &amp;c.</hi> Home is home though never ſo homely. Hence it was that <hi>Hadad</hi> in another caſe, (1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 21, 22) deſired of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that <hi>he might go home to his [own] Countrey, though he had lacked nothing in Egypt, yet he would go home in any wiſe.</hi> Chriſt in the Goſpel calleth the ſinner to the forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his own kindred, and his fathers houſe; all its own ways, relations, and concernments whatſoever. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that though Chriſt doth make never ſuch rich profers to the ſinner, yet here he ſticks (till overcome by Almighty power) he can't leave home, he loveth his own ways, and muſt walk in them, though he periſh eternally. It's for this cauſe that the Fathers of the Antichriſtian Church, cannot be content to worſhip God according to their own brains themſelves, but (according to their power) will force it upon others: The reaſon is, becauſe it is framed by their grace, wiſdom, and underſtanding, and all of it the work of the Crafts-men; and therefore ſay they, let the men that ſacrifice kiſs the Calf, bovv and ſtoop to our Image, and that upon pain of death, or baniſhment; ſee for this <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13. 2. Oh! hovv earneſt hath this made perſons at Idolatry, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 18. But</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 2. Man is a creature that naturally doth love eaſe; novv this broad vvay is an eaſie path, there is nothing of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it. As the vvay of ignorance is an eaſie path. To live as thouſands even in this Iſland do, vvho content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vvith the bare coming to Church, and being at Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and never take no pains in ſearching after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God; pleaſing themſelves with this conceit, that becauſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101421:19"/> they want that education which others have, God expects not that they ſhould trouble themſelves about ſearching the Scriptures, or about the various Opinions of men in the Worſhip of God; and ſo contents themſelves, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they are under the glorious light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel) do live and dye in ignorance. And there is a Miniſtry in the World that ſuits this ſpirit, that teacheth the people that they need trouble themſelves no further about Religion, ſave onely to attend conſtantly upon Divine Service, and to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant at the Sacrament when it is adminiſtred, and get ſome good Prayer-Book to read in their Families <note n="*" place="margin">Mind here, that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt work of Religion is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal work, pulling down the ſtrong holds of the heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It lieth in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation &amp; mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ification, and without this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k be done, people m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y go to hel for all their Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and good Prayer Books</note>. Now this being an eaſie Religion, it's greatly pleaſing, and many poor ignorant people wil thank a Miniſter at preſent that ſhal ſo inſtruct them, though it may be they may curſe him hereafter in Hell for it. <hi>2dly,</hi> The way of prophaneneſs, an eaſie path; a man may ſit upon an Ale-Bench and be drunk, lye upon a Down-bed and be unclean, ſit upon a Couch and ſwear, and curſe, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the Name of God, and reproach his people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo alſo for the Negative Chriſtian, the Will-worſhipper, and the Hypocrite. None of theſe come ſo far as to pull out a right eye, or cut off a right hand for God. Sin may be loved, yea practiſed either more openly, or more ſecretly in all theſe paths</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Here's peace (ſuch as it is) enjoyed in this broad way. It's true, God ſpeaks not peace to a wicked man, but the Devil he doth, Luke 11. 21. <hi>When a ſtrong man armed keepeth his Palace, his Goods are in peace.</hi> The ſoul of an unregenerate man is the Devil's habitation; and it's the great deſign of the Devil to guard the ſoul, and to preſerve its ſinful peace, and to prevent whatever might diſturb it. And herein doth a wicked man join with the Devil, being very loath to have his peace broken. Hence it is that wicked men do ſo hate and abhor a ſoul-ſearching-Miniſter, a burning and a ſhining light; the reaſon is, becauſe ſuch a Miniſtry hath a tendency to break this helliſh peace. It's therefore the Devils buſineſs to furniſh thoſe of his Subjects, (which muſt needs have ſome kind of preaching) with ſuch a Miniſtry as ſhall neither by preaching nor living, diſturb their peace. Thoſe then that do employ themſelves to thruſt out Labourers, and to put in Loyterers; to thruſt out ſuch who endeavour to ſearch to the quick, and bring in ſuch as will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101421:19"/> daub with untempered morter, do the Devil the beſt ſervice of any men in the world.</p>
            <p>But note, that before ever the ſoul comes to enjoy true peace of Conſcience, this ſinful peace muſt be deſtroyed. Chriſt comes not (in the Goſpel) to maintain, but to deſtroy this peace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>4thly,</hi> Man is a ſociable creature, and loves company; and in this broad way the Devil can furniſh them with all ſorts of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates ſuitable to his diſpoſition. As,</p>
            <p>1. Art thou a plain Countrey-man that loves to talk of thy Ploughing and ſowing, &amp;c. but doſt not fancy to diſcourſe of Religion; thou thinkeſt that Diſcourſe is fit onely for Miniſters or learned Gentlemen, and not for ſuch plain men as thy ſelf. The Devil can furniſh thee with very ſuitable company; for he hath thouſands in his Kingdom that do regard Religion as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as thou doſt. Or,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Art thou a ranting, damning fellow, that is reſolved for a merry life, though a ſhort one; to ſatifie thy luſt to the full; and that never a <hi>Phanatique</hi> in the world ſhall alter thy mind, or ſtop thee in this Carear: That let what will come of it, thou art reſolved to have thy Whores, Cups, Oaths, &amp;c. The Devil hath company for thee alſo. I am apt to think, that at this day the Devil hath more of this ſort in his Kingdom then pleaſeth him, they being grown now to that paſs, that they cannot be ſatisfied to have their fill of wickedneſs, but they muſt abuſe ſuch as will not run with them into the ſame exceſs. Now the Devil hath ſuch in his Kingdom, that though they do not hate ſuch things upon Gods account, (for then they would hate all ſin) yet their very Couſtitutions and Educations leads them to abhor them. And theſe perſons being a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted<note place="margin">Pſal. 31. 20</note> by the debauched party in the Devils Kingdom, may haply be convinced, and put upon it to look after a Pavillion, wherein they may be kept from the ſtrife of Tongues *: For ſomething that may down-weigh that reproach and malignity that this helliſh party doth caſt upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Art thou for civil company? The Devil hath of theſe alſo in his Kingdom, perſons that are well bred, and that do ſcorn to abuſe any, doth abhor a prophane diſſolute Carriage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> Art thou one, that though thou loveſt not to be over-preciſe, to be tied up to hard meat, yet (having ſome notions of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101421:20"/> immortality) canſt not be content without ſome kind of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p, thou art therefore for a good honeſt merry Religion, that Religion that hath been of late years, is too melancholly for thee, it makes thee no Muſick; and thou art for a Miniſter that is a good fellow, that won't preach too often, and when he doth, not be too earneſt, but will now and then break a jeſt in the Pulpit; and when he hath done preaching, wil not preſs you ſo much to private devotion, but that you may after Sermon upon Sunday (as you call it) fetch a walk in the fields, and play a game or two at nine-pins, or at bowls, &amp;c. In this broad way there are many of thy ſpirit in this alſo. And this let me tell thee, That it ſhall not be the Devils fault, nor the fault of his ſervants, if thou art not fitted with a Religion that ſhall ſuit thee; a Religion that ſhall (1.) be eaſie to underſtand. <hi>2dly,</hi> To perform, <hi>3dly,</hi> That ſhall indulge thy luſts ſufficiently. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly,</hi> Art thou paſt all the former, and art not onely for ſome Worſhip, but a pure Worſhip? Will no company pleaſe thee but Virgins, ſuch as have not defiled themſelves with pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Worſhip? Give but heed to the Devil, and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le help thee to diſſemble, and by diſſimulation to get in among Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it may be into Church-fellowſhip; &amp; when thou art there (carrying thy ſelf cloſely) a thouſand to one but in a little time the Devil will help thee to the ſociety of ſome in that Church that have as vain a ſpirit as thy ſelf, and ſo you may walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (concealing the matter) not onely in the love, but practiſe of abominable wickedneſs, under a great profeſſion. Now there being ſuch accommodation for company in the Devils Kingdom, is a fourth Reaſon why ſo many walk in it. But,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> Laſtly; The laſt Reaſon is, Becauſe that thoſe which are walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this path, know not whither they are going: Should you tell ſuch perſons that they are going the way to Hell, they'l not believe you; they'l tell you you that they hope to be ſaved as well as the beſt, and that they never in all their lives did queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mercy of God. It's true, every man hath his failings, and ſo have they; but God is abundant in mercy, and Chriſt he came to dye for ſinners; and they wonder why any perſon ſhould que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the mercy of God, and the pardon of their ſins; they bleſs God they never did queſtion it ſince they were born. Now as God is the Father of a Chriſtians hope (1 Pet. 1. 3—<hi>begotten us again
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101421:20"/> to a lively hope</hi>) and it hath all its nouriſhment from Heaven; ſo a wicked man's hope it's begotten by the Devil, and nouriſhed by the breaſt of Hell, and ſo long as the Devil can preſerve this hope of happineſs (notwithſtanding a ſinful life) the ſoul is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; but when once this wretched hope is deſtroyed, then the Devils Kingdom in the ſoul begins to ſhake. For the Kingdom of Chriſt (his Rule and Dominion in the ſoul) is built upon the ruines of this accurſed Hope. Alas! were but a wicked man ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his Eſtate, he could not reſt ſatisfied one hour; but they are infatuated, under the power of an <hi>Aegyptian</hi> darkneſs, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differing from the darkneſs of <hi>Aegypt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 10 21</note> in this, that they fell it not, are not ſenſible of it. And hence it is that the Devil's Kingdom is ſo full.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt particular propoſed, namely, That the way that leadeth to everlaſting ruine, is a broad, eaſie way.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be ſpoken to (in the handling of which<note place="margin">The <hi>2d.</hi> doct <hi>That the way to Heaven is a ſtrait narrow way.</hi>
               </note> we ſhall but hint things) is, <hi>That the way to glory and everlaſting bleſſedneſs, is aſtrait narrow way.</hi> I ſhall (for the diſpatch of this) endeavour to make a two-fold diſcovery, and that in a very ſummary, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What the way to true bleſſedneſs is.</item>
               <item>2. What the reaſon is it's ſo ſtraight and narrow.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the ſolution of the firſt, I ſhall onely give you this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral<note place="margin">What the way to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is.</note> anſwer, That it is the way of Faith in Chriſt, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Chriſt. Of faith in Chriſt, whereby the ſoul goeth out of its ſelf, and reſteth alone upon the free-grace of God in Chriſt for ſalvation. Of obedience, whereby the ſoul receiving Chriſt as a Lord and King, is made willing to ſubject to all his Commandments, deſiring to own and obey (in the ſtrength of God) whatever it finds to have the ſtamp of his Authority up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. Theſe two (Faith and Obedience) taken in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are paths that will undoubtedly lead to everlaſting glory. Indeed that faith that is without obedience, is a dead faith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2 And on the other hand, that obedience that is without faith, is unacceptable, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. But in what ſoul ſoever there is ſuch a faith as doth produce obedience, and ſuch an obedience as is the fruit of true faith, that ſoul is bleſt at preſent, and ſhall be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101421:21"/> bleſt unto Eternity. And this is all I ſhall ſay in anſwer to the firſt query: The ſecond follows.<note place="margin">What it is that maketh Heavens way ſo ſtrait.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The ſecond thing to be diſcovered is, What it is that maketh the way to glory ſo ſtreight and narrow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It ariſeth not from any thing in the way it ſelf; for all the wayes of Wiſdom <hi>are wayes of pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are peace</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 3. 19</note>. Chriſt's <hi>yoke it is eaſie, and his burthen light</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Matt. 11.</note>. And <hi>his commands they are not grievous</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Iohn 5. 3.</note>. But from that contrariety and oppoſition that there is not onely in the unconverted, but alſo in the unregenerated part of thoſe that are converted againſt thoſe terms which Chriſt hath propounded for all thoſe that will be his Diſciples, to ſubmit unto. The ſinner would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſt gladly, ſo he might have him upon his own terms; but now all thoſe that do expect benefit by Chriſt, they muſt<note place="margin">Chriſt his terms.</note> ſubmit to thoſe terms that Chriſt hath propoſed; which terms are expreſſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 23. And he ſaid to them all, If any man will come after me, let him.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Deny himſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Take up his Croſs daily.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>And follow me.</hi> Now theſe terms being ſo contrary to fleſh and blood, hence it is that it is ſo hard a matter to be a true Diſciple of Chriſt. I ſhall therefore for the further clearing of this diſcovery, ſpeak ſomething touching each of theſe terms propoſed by Chriſt. And<note place="margin">About ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>1. For that of ſelf-denial: I ſhall</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Give you a more general deſcription of it. And</item>
               <item>2. Shall ſhew you more particularly what it is that Chriſt doth call the ſinner to deny.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Take the general deſcription thus: <hi>Self-denial, is a gracious</hi>
               <note place="margin">Self-denial deſcribed.</note> 
               <hi>work of the Spirit of God, enabling the ſoul by Faith, ſo to behold the glory and excellency of Chriſt, as to deny its ſelf, and all ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, as they are either compared to Chriſt, or elſe come in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſtand to open the parts of this Deſcription (for<note place="margin">What Chriſt call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the ſinner to deny</note> that would take up too much time, and alſo encreaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſheets above my intent) but ſhall (according to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) ſhew you in a few particulars what it is that Chriſt calls the ſinner to deny. And</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101421:21"/>
            <p>1. He calls him to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſt, to<note place="margin">1. Sin.</note> part with every ſin, yea even ſuch ſins that may be as a right eye, or a right hand, <hi>Matth. 5. 29. Tit.</hi> 2. 12, 14. There muſt be forſaking of all ſin, as to the love of it, and delight in it. A wicked man may (for baſe ends) refrain ſin, and yet love it; and a good man may commit ſin, and yet hate it. But note here, it's not the preſence of ſin, ſo much as the love of ſin, that damns the ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> He calls the ſoul to deny all natural and acquired parto,<note place="margin">2 Natural and acquired parts</note> as a meek, well-tempered nature, an humble, lowly carriage, good education, ſchool-learning, &amp;c. Theſe things are not ſo to be denyed, as (1.) not to bleſs God for them. And <hi>2dly,</hi> not to improve them; but they are ſo to be denyed, as that we ſhould not look upon our ſelves to be ever the more deſerving the love and favour of God becauſe of theſe endowments. And <hi>2dly,</hi> That we ſhould not reſt in theſe qualifications, placing our happineſs in them, and not coming to Chriſt, in whom alone is true perfection, 1 <hi>Cor. 1. 21—The world by [Wiſdom] knew not God.</hi> The learned of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> were too wiſe to cloſe with Chriſt, and to hearken to the fooliſh preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. And therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Cap. 3. ver. 18. He that would be wiſe, he muſt become a fool.</hi> The onely way to obtain ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Wiſdom, is to deny our natural and acquired parts, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o know our ſelves to be fools.<note place="margin">3 All Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> We are called to deny all our Religious performances, uch as preaching, hearing, praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to deny all in point of Juſtification from the guilt of ſin, and acceptation into Gods favour, <hi>Iſa. 64. 6. Phil.</hi> 3. 7, 8, 9: We are to perform religious duties with that care and diligence, as if we were to obtain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life by our works; and yet on the other hand, we are to reſt upon the free grace of God in Chriſt for ſalvation, as if we had never done one good work, never performed one good duty</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> All Ordinances and external priviledges are alſo to be<note place="margin">4 Ordinances &amp; priviledges.</note> denyed, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 1. Wo to them that are at eaſe (not in <hi>Sodom,</hi> but) in <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's a great mercy to enjoy Ordinances; they are of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to a people <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, but if thou doſt reſt in bare Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without the enjoyment of the God of Ordinances, they'l
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101421:22"/> leave thee ſhort of heaven at laſt, as they did the fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>Math.</hi> 25. See alſo <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 22, 23. Ordinances are but as the Caſement through which the light doth ſhine, as the Diſh in which the Meat is brought, as the Pipe through w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Water doth run. Now can you imagine, that a man that is not blinde, can be content with a Caſement without Light? or a Hungry man, with a Diſh wherein is no meat? or a Thirſty man, with a Pipe through which doth run no Water? And yet ſuch is the madneſs of thoſe that pleaſe themſelves with hearing Sermons, &amp; receiving Sacraments, reſting in theſe things, notwithſtanding they remain in an ignorant, vile, and wretched eſtate, without the experience of ought that hath been preacht to them in the Word, or repreſented to them in the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>5. Chriſt calls to the denying of all worldly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<note place="margin">5. All wordly concernments, as</note> whatſoever, in compariſon of, or in competition with himſelf, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Riches;</hi> Jer. 9. 23. Pſal. 62. 10. 1 Tim. 6. 17. Heb. 11.<note place="margin">1. Riches.</note> 26. It's a hard matter for a man to be rich in this world, and not to truſt in his riches, and therefore it is that it's ſo hard for a rich man to enter into heaven, <hi>Math.</hi> 19. 23. compared with <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 24. where Chriſt by the rich man declareth his meaning to be of thoſe that truſt in riches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Honour;</hi> Chriſt in this is propoſed for our enſample,<note place="margin">2. Honor.</note> Phil. 2. 7. <hi>made himſelf of no reputation.</hi> The Apoſtles (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 13.) were content to be defamed, made <hi>as the filth and off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world.</hi> Heb. 11. 24, 25, 26. There <hi>Moſes</hi> deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and trampled upon the glory and honour of the Court, and of being called the Son of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter. A good name is a precious ointment, but ſometimes a perſon may fall into this <hi>dilemma,</hi> that either he muſt be diſhoneſt, or be ſo accounted, be a fanatick in name, or in truth: It then ſavours of an excellent ſpirit, when a perſon ſhall chooſe rather to be accounted diſhoneſt, then to be diſhoneſt; chooſe rather to be called a fanatick, then to be ſo.<note place="margin">3 Relations &amp; Habitations</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Relations</hi> &amp; <hi>Habitations;</hi> Relations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 37. compared with <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 26. there you'l finde that our love to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations muſt be a hatred, compared with our love to Chriſt.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101421:22"/> Habitations, <hi>Gen. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Pſal. 45. 10. Heb. 11. 8. Math. 19. 28. Mark 10. 29, 30. Luke</hi> 18. 29, 30.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Pleaſures;</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 4. We muſt take heed of loving<note place="margin">4 Pleaſures.</note> pleaſures more then God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 13. It's the love of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that doth occaſion the breach of the Sabbath. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent example of this part of Self-denial we have in <hi>Moſes,</hi> Heb. 11. 25. <hi>Chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. There muſt be a denying our ſelves in reſpect of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries<note place="margin">5. In reſpect of Injuries offered.</note> offered; we muſt not ſeek revenge, nor return evil for evil, but on the contrary bleſs them that curſe us, &amp;c. <hi>Math. 5. Rom. 12. 14, 19, 20, 21. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 23.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>In Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks;</hi> we are not to eat and drink in<note place="margin">6. Meats and Drinks. 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 31.</hi>
               </note> exceſs, to ſurfeting and drunkenneſs, but to uſe moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, making the ſervice and glory of God our great end in the uſe of his creatures, <hi>Prov. 23. 1, 2, 3. Rom. 13. 13. 1 Cor. 9. 27. Eph. 5. 18. Luke 21. 34. Phil.</hi> 3. 19.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Life it ſelf;</hi> as father and mother, brother and ſiſter,<note place="margin">7. Life it ſelf.</note> &amp;c. are to be hated in compariſon of Chriſt, ſo is even life it ſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 26. And the onely way to keep life here with a bleſſing, and enjoy an eternal life in glory, is to be willing to reſigne up our ſelves, and all that we have and are to the cauſe of Chriſt, when ever Chriſt ſhall call us ſo to do. Our Lord Chriſt hath ſaid it once and again: <hi>Whoſoever will ſave his life ſhall loſe it; but whoſoever ſhall loſe his life for my ſake and the Gospel, the ſame ſhall ſave it: and what profit will it be for a man to gain the whole world and loſe his ſoul?</hi> Math. 10. 39. &amp; 16 25, 26. Mark 8. 35, 36, 37. Luke 9. 24. 25.</p>
            <p>And thus much touching the firſt term, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-denyal; the ſecond follows, which is</p>
            <p>2. <hi>That every Diſciple muſt take up hit Croſs daily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall here <hi>firſt</hi> ſhew you what this Croſs is; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> what it is to take up this Croſs.</p>
            <p>1. By <hi>Croſs</hi> ſometimes is underſtood the efficacy &amp; power<note place="margin">What the Croſs of Chriſt is.</note> of Chriſts Death, as 1 <hi>Cor. 1. 17, 18. Gal. 6. 14. Col.</hi> 2. 14. and ſometimes Affliction and Perſecution, ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. and ſo are we to underſtand it here in this Scripture. A Chriſtian he hath many Croſſes in this world, as that of Sin, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101421:23"/> Deſertion, &amp;c. but that which Chriſt chiefly doth here intend, is doubtleſs that of Perſecution. There are four places wherein Chriſt propoundeth this term, namely, <hi>Math.</hi> 10 30: &amp; 16. 24. <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 34: and this in <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 23. In <hi>Math</hi> 10. he ſpake largely touching what they ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from men, and then in the cloſe telleth them, <hi>That he that takeih not his Croſs and followeth him, is not worthy of him;</hi> that is, whoſoever ſhall decline him, or his way, by reaſon of that Croſs of perſecution he had afore-mentioned, that perſon was not worthy of him. And in the three other places, he was in each of them ſhewing to his Diſciples what great things he was to ſuffer of the Elders and chief Prieſts at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> being ſomewhat offended and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it, Chriſt rebuketh him, and declareth in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the people, and of his Diſciples, <hi>That whoſoever would come after him muſt take up his Croſs.</hi> Hereby clearly ſhewing to all his Diſciples, that the ſame ſpirit of envy and hatred that was in the world againſt him, will be againſt them alſo, <hi>Math 10. 23, 24, 25. Joh.</hi> 15. 18, 19, 20. and therefore they muſt reſolve to follow him, bearing their Croſs. There is a Croſs of Perſecution and Tribulation to be born in a leſſer<note place="margin">Such an enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Seeds, that nothing can be expected but perſecution from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the world. See <hi>Gen 3. 15. Gal 4. 29. Prov. 29. ult. Iohn 16. ult.</hi>
               </note> or greater meaſure by all the Saints in this world, <hi>Joh. 16. ult. Acts 14 22. Phil.</hi> 1. 29. &amp; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 12. there the Apoſtle ſaith, All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer Perſecution. It's poſſible ſome carnal formal Profeſſors may rub out in perſecuting times; but ſuch as are <hi>godly in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> ſuch as walk by Goſpel-light, and according to Goſpel-rule, they ſhall be ſure to ſuffer perſecution. Every unregenerate man is more or leſs a perſecutor, and therefore while the Saints do live in this world among wicked and ungodly men, they will in a greater or leſſer meaſure be tormented and perſecuted by the world.</p>
            <p>But what is it to take up this Croſs?</p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer to this both Negatively and Affirmatively,<note place="margin">What the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up of the Croſs is. 1. Negatively.</note> what we are not to underſtand, and then what we are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Negatively;</hi> We are not to underſtand any kinde of reverence to be given, either to the Image, or ſigne of the Croſs. The bearing of the image of the Croſs is a place of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101421:23"/> great honor among the Papiſts, who do greatly adore and reverence the ſame: And ſo alſo they do the Sign of the Croſs, giving the Signe no leſs honor then the Image; but herein they are certainly (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the Athenians) too ſuperſtitious, there being no rule in the Word of God for ſuch Adoration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt in propounding this term, doth (as it ſeemeth to me) ſecretly inhibite his people the making &amp; creating a Croſs to themſelves. As wicked men are apt to ſay, Peace, Peace, when there is no Peace; ſo Gods own people are apt to fear when no fear is, and to create trouble and ſorrow to themſelves. For the Devil, if he can't intice the ſoul from the waies of God, then will he endeavour to diſcourage it, by perſwading it that there is a Lion in the way. That it will never be able to hold out, and hold on in heavens way, there is ſuch vallies of death, and mountains of difficulties to paſs thorow &amp; go over. Now though Chriſt would have the Soul to perſevere in his commands, whatever the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty be he meets withall, yet he would not have it give heed to ſuch amazing and perplexing ſuggeſtions, but by faith to live above them, And thus by way of Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For the Affirmative, I ſhall anſwer it in theſe four parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:<note place="margin">2. Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</note> To take up the Croſs is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Soul deliberately, after ſerious debates in the heart about this matter, to reſolve (in the ſtrength of God) to hold on in heavens-way, let what will come, Diſgrace, Poverty, Impriſonment, Fire and Fagot, &amp;c. with <hi>Job</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, <hi>Though he kill mee, yet I'le truſt him</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iob 13. 15.</note>. A Hypocrite may reſolve high, but his reſolves are uſually ſudden and paſſionate reſolves, and ſo come to little: but now a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans reſolves (when he acts like himſelf) are deliberate and ſincere reſolves, depending not upon his own but the ſtrength of God, and theſe reſolves hold; and though a Chriſtian (that hath ſo reſolved) may live and dye in a calm ſeaſon, and ſuffer little, (comparatively) yet God (who knoweth the heart) accepteth the will for the deed,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101421:24"/> and taketh it as kindely as if he had ſuffered abundantly more for his name and glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is to acquieſce in Gods pleaſure, to have our wills reſolved into the will of God, quietly to ſubmit under all his diſpenſations and providences, though ſeemingly they may contradict his promiſes and our expectations: with the Church (<hi>Micah</hi> 7. 9) to reſolve <hi>the bearing his indignation, untill he plead our cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. That ſoul doth truly &amp; rightly bear his Croſs, that doth quietly ſubmit himſelf to God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all afflictions, being (in <hi>Davids</hi> ſenſe) <hi>dumb, not opening his mouth, becauſe it is the Lords doings</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 39. 9.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To take up this Croſs, is to do it cheerfully, to do it upon choice; for ſo Chriſt propoundeth this term, that whoſoever will chooſe him to be his Lord and Saviour, muſt chooſe the Croſs alſo; will chooſe to reign with him, muſt alſo chooſe to ſuffer with him. A hypocrite may ſuffer much upon the account of Religion, but he ſuffers not upon choice; could he preſerve his name, or bring about ſome ſuch ſiniſter end, he would never ſuffer; his ſuffering for truth is not out of love to truth, but upon ſome other baſe and low account. But now <hi>Moſes</hi> he ſuffered much, and that upon choice, he choſe rather to ſuffer with Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then to enjoy ſinfull pleaſures <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11. 25.</note>. Chriſts yoke is not put on <hi>per</hi> force, we are to take his yoke and burthen upon us, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt particular (which acquainteth us rather with the manner then the matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the duty) is, that to take up this Croſs, is to perſevere, to hold out to the end. <hi>He muſt deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs [daily.</hi>] We muſt not be weary of ſuffering for Chriſt, or Truth, but after we have ſuffered reproach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſcorn, then we muſt be willing to ſuffer confiſcation of Goods, after that Impriſonment, and after that Baniſhment, and after that cruel Death, <hi>Math. 10. 22. And ye ſhall be hated of all men for my Names ſake; but he that endureth to the end ſhall be ſaved.</hi> And thus I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched the ſecond term, <hi>viz.</hi> The taking up the Croſs.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt is, <hi>to follow Chriſt.</hi> Now we are to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low<note place="margin">We are to follow Chriſt</note>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:101421:24"/> Chriſt, 1. In his Commands, 2. Examples, and 3. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his Commands; to follow Chriſt, is to obey him,<note place="margin">1. In his Commands.</note> 
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 4, 5, 27. The true Sheep follow the true Shepherd, and will not follow ſtrangers; that is, they hear and obey the voice of Chriſt, and his onely, they will not hear nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obey the voice of Strangers. In this term is required then, that the ſoul do heartily and ſincerely own Chriſt for it's Lord and K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, to be ruled and governed by him, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him alone for the Lord of it's conſcience, and obeying him (at le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt in deſire and affection) in all his commands, ſo farr as they are revealed and diſcovered unto the ſoul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are to follow Chriſt in his Examples. Chriſt was<note place="margin">2. In his Examples</note> not in all things our Example; for ſome things he did by the power of his God-head, and therein he was not an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to us; and ſomething he did as Mediator, <hi>viz.</hi> ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Fathers wrath, and purchaſe eternal life for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and herein he was not an Example, Heb. 1. 3.—<hi>When he had [by himſelf] purged our ſins, ſate down on the right hand of the Majeſty on high:</hi> but in that holineſs and righteouſneſs that did appear in him, therein he was our Example, <hi>Math. 11. 29. Learn of me:</hi> What is it we ſhould learn? Not to raiſe the Dead, open the eyes of the Blinde, &amp;c. but <hi>to be meek and lowly.</hi> Every true Chriſtian was predeſtinated to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to this Pattern, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. and called unto it, 1 Pet. 2. 21, 22, 23. <hi>For even hereunto were ye called: becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps. Who did no ſin, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Whoſoever ſaith he abideth in him, ought himſelf ſo to walk, even as he walked,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 6. A true Chriſtian is then to take Chriſt for its great &amp; high Example, to conſider how Chriſt carried it <hi>firſt</hi> with reſpect to the world, and all the enjoyments thereof, how he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed and humbled himſelf; and then <hi>ſecondly</hi> how he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed it with reſpect to Satan, when under his temptations, how he defended Satan, not with this or that notion, nor yet with this or that experience, but with a <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> 
               <hi>It is written.</hi> The ſword of the Spirit is the beſt Weapon to fight the Devil with. And then <hi>thirdly</hi> how Chriſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101421:25"/> it towards men, both Saints and Sinners; how loving, and meek, and graciouſly diſpoſed he was to all: and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how he carried it towards his Father; how he obeyed, how zealouſly, how chearfully, how exactly; he did not onely do what was commanded, but as it was commanded, <hi>Joh 14. ult.</hi> how fully fulfilling all righteouſneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 15. how conſtantly he began in the morning of his age, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 42 to the 50. and continued until he had finiſhed his whole work: And then how he believed, and how he prayed; and laſtly how he carried it under ſufferings, when upon the Croſs, in that great torment, he crieth not out, Oh my hands, or my ſides; but, <hi>Oh my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> The withdrawings of God was more to him then all his ſufferings. Now in ſuch things as theſe, is the Chriſtian to write after this pattern, to walk (according as he is able) even as Chriſt walked.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We are to follow Chriſt in his Providences. To follow<note place="margin">3. In his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. <hi>Rev. 14 4.</hi>
               </note> the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth. Now we may be ſaid to follow Chriſt in his Providences, when we do, 1. Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge God in them, ſee and acknowledge the hand of God in all providential diſpenſations; and 2. Quietly ſubmit to God's hand, and not with that wicked man, to ſay, <hi>This evil is of the Lord, why ſhould I wait any longer upon him?</hi> But<note place="margin">2 Kings 6. 33.</note> how croſs ſoever Providences may be, even to the promiſe of God, yet to reſt upon the faithfulneſs of him that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and to believe that God will moſt certainly make good all that he hath ſpoken concerning the glory of his Sons Kingdom. And laſtly, then do we follow Chriſt in his Providences, when we do hear and obey the call of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Now the call of Providence is not always the ſame; ſomtimes it calls for Thankſgiving, &amp; ſomtimes for Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſometimes for doing, and ſometimes for ſuffering; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to bear a teſtimony to one Truth and Way of Chriſt, and ſometimes to another. So that then do we follow Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt in his Providence, when we do hear, underſtand, and obey the voice of Providence, doing that which the preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God doth call for.</p>
            <p>Thus have I briefly ſhewed what thoſe terms are that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101421:25"/> Chriſt hath propounded to all that will be his Diſciples. Whereby you may ſee the reaſon, why it is that ſo few walk in the way of life, It's becauſe they cannot ſtoop to theſe terms. Naturally men are engaged to their luſts, and their own ways, and theſe they will ſerve and follow, though they venture the loſs of their ſouls by it. And hence it is alſo, that God's own people find it ſo hard a matter to keep cloſe with God; the reaſon is from that averſeneſs that is in the unregenerate part unto Chriſt's commands: So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſoul hath freely and heartily cloſed with Chriſt upon his own terms; yet oft times when it comes to the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, it's forced to cry out with <hi>Paul,</hi> that to will is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent<note place="margin">Rom. 7. 18.</note> *. The Lord knows my heart is right with him; but how to obey, how to paſs over this difficulty, how to perform this duty, how to take up this croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I cannot tell.</p>
            <p>I have now finiſhed what I ſhall ſay to the Doctrinal part of both propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That the way to deſtruction is broad and eaſie. And <hi>2dly,</hi> That the way to happineſs is ſtraight and narrow. I ſhall winde up the whole with four vvords of application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may ſerve by vvay of Information, to inform us of<note place="margin">The Uſe. 1. Of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> the great reaſon vvhy ſo many that do profeſs the Name of Chriſt, fall from their profeſſion. The reaſon is, becauſe they did never cordially and heartily receive Chriſt upon the terms before-mentioned; took not up their profeſſion out of love to Chriſt, but upon ſome other baſe and lovv account, and in the midſt of all their profeſſion had their hearts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to one curſed luſt or other, vvhich they could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for Chriſt, And mind this, that that profeſſion vvhich is<note place="margin">Note.</note> taken up in hypocriſie, a thouſand to one but it ends in apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy; as every you vvould perſevere in Heavens vvay, labour to be ſincere and upright vvith God,</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe is of Caution, and that in two reſpects.<note place="margin">2. Of Cautio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 1. Take heed of walking ſecurely in any path upon this account that the moſt walk in it, ſince you ſee that the moſt of the world walk in the broad way that leadeth to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. To do as the moſt do, is to damn your ſouls: to trifle away your day of grace, until your glaſs be run, and your
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101421:26"/> ſun be ſet, and everlaſting flames about your ears. Say not that this or that way of worſhip is moſt acceptable to God, becauſe it is accepted and approved of by the moſt of men; for that way of worſhip which God requires (that is, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual worſhip) is not known by, or beloved of the moſt of the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed of diſowning the way of Chriſt, becauſe of the paucity of thoſe that walk therein. This was that which made the Sodomites to deſpiſe <hi>Lot</hi> and his counſel, <hi>Gen. 19. 9. This [one] fellow</hi> (ſay they) <hi>came in to ſojourn amongſt us, and he will needs be a Judge.</hi> If there had been hundreds of <hi>Lot's</hi> mind, haply they would have been more ready to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined; but he being alone, they looked upon him as an odd fellow, one that was brain-ſick, that had a Fanatick ſpirit, and therefore regarded not what he ſpake. God's people they are a very ſmal remnant, as a lodge in a Garden of Cucumbers, there is no cluſter in them, as the gleanings after the Vintage is over. * It may be here and there but<note place="margin">Iſa. 1 8, 9 Mic. 7. 1</note> one in a great family that doth own the way of Chriſt, and and that it may be a child, or a poor ſervant. A few in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and they it may be the poorer ſort; and hereupon the men of the world do deſpiſe, and trample upon the holy ways of Chriſt. Perſons in matters of Religion, do general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolve to do as the moſt and greateſt of men do, though they ſuffer everlaſtingly for it. As you love your ſouls take heed of ſtumbling at this ſtumbling-ſtone.</p>
            <p>The third uſe is of trial, If the way to deſtruction be broad,<note place="margin">A uſe of trial.</note> and the way to life narrow, then it concerns every one thus to reaſon with his ſoul; O my ſoul! in which of theſe two paths doſt thou walk? Art thou bound for Heaven, or Hell? What will become of thee, when thou ſhalt leave this houſe of clay, <note place="margin">Arguments to enforce exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note> and lanch forth into the great Ocean of Eternity? How will it fare with thee in the other world? Conſider of the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this duty in theſe four particulars</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> In one of theſe two paths do all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> walk. There are but two eſtates in that Eternity that is before thee, the one everlaſtingly bleſſed, and the other everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly miſerable and thou art haſting to one of theſe eſtates;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101421:26"/> every motion of thy ſoul is a motion towards Eternity; and ſo ſoon as ever thou comeſt to dye, thou wilt either enter into the joy of the bleſſed, or elſe be a companion for damned Spirits, and reſerved under chains of darkneſs, unto the judgement of the great day. While thou art in this world, thou art either a believer or an unbeliever, a Child of God, or a Child of the Devil; in the Kingdom of Chriſt, or in the Kingdom of Satan: Chriſt's friend, or his enemy: And when thou leaveſt this world, thou muſt either be bleſſed with the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> or curſt with the ſeed of <hi>Cain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The Scriptures tell us there are but a very few that will enter in at the ſtrait gate. Now if the Scriptures had declared that all mankinde ſhould have been ſaved except ten perſons thou mighteſt have feared thy ſelf to have been one of thoſe ten: But when on the other hand, the Scriptures ſhall ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare, that the moſt will be damned, and but a few ſaved, how is it then that thou canſt eat and ſleep in peace, plow and ſow in peace, and the ſalvation of thy precious ſoul be at ſuch uncertainties?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Conſider how many thouſands have been miſtaken in this great buſineſs; who in the time of their health and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, have been very confident of mercy and ſalvation, and of Gods love to their ſouls: how hath ſuch a ſoul ſaid of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-priviledges, <hi>Theſe are mine?</hi> Of the promiſe of pardon, <hi>This is mine?</hi> Of peace and joy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Theſe are mine?</hi> Of Divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, <hi>This is mine?</hi> And yet when ſuch have come to dye, have found nothing theirs but their ſin, and God's wrath. Yea, how at the laſt they ſhall come knocking at Heaven's Gate, and demand entrance, ſaying, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us,</hi> but ſhall find the gate everlaſtingly ſhut upon them, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22, 23. &amp; 25. 11, 12. For Chriſt ſake (therefore) take heed of a groundleſs confidence of God's love, and thine own ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>4thly,</hi> If thou dyeſt under ſuch a miſtake, thou art eternally loſt. If ſin be thy burden now, the Scriptures tells thee where thou maiſt have eaſe, upon whom thou maiſt caſt this burden; but if thou ſhalt not feel the burden of ſin till thou droppeſt into H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, (for there thou wilt be ſure to feel it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with a witneſs) then it will be too late; there will then be no remedy,</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:101421:27"/>
            <p>Queſt, <hi>How may I do that I may know the ſtate and condition of my ſoul, as to this great matter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the handling of the firſt Doctrine we made a fivefold<note place="margin">How to come to know the true ſtate of our ſouls.</note> diſcovery of the broad way to Hell, and have ſhewn, that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, prophaneneſs, diſobedience, will-worſhip, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, are all paths that do lead into the Chambers of death. I would therefore in the firſt place propoſe, that thou wouldſt conſider of this diſcovery by way of tryal, as thus: 1. Examine whether thou art not yet in a ſtate of ignorance. This is a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damning path. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor. 4. 3) its hid to them that are loſt.</hi> What knowledge haſt thou of thy wretched eſtate by nature? Of the free and abſolute Covenant of Grace ſealed in the blood of Chriſt? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I muſt here be plain. I am greatly afraid that many of you are ſo far from knowing theſe things experimentally, in the myſtery of them, that you are ſtrangers to the notion, and hiſtory of them. Now though we may know the Hiſtory, and be ſtrangers to the Myſtery; yet its impoſſible we ſhould know theſe things in the myſterie, and by experience, and not know them notionally. The myſterie is wrapt up in the Hiſtory. The precious word of the Goſpel is the field in which this Pearl is hid, the ſwadling cloaths in which the Babe is wrapped: So that there can be no receiving of, or believing in the Lord Chriſt without ſome knowledge of him as declared and diſcovered in the Scriptures. <hi>2dly,</hi> Thou ſpeakeſt of God's love and mercy; examine, it may be thou art to be found in the path of a debauched life; it may be thou maiſt be found to be a drunkard, a ſwearer, a ſabbath-breaker, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of God and his people, a ſcoffer at the wayes of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to live in the practiſe of ſuch things as theſe; and not onely ſo, but to take pleaſure in them that do them, <hi>Rom. 1. ult.</hi> Now conſider, how canſt thou call thy ſelf a Chriſtian, and live after this rate? What, a Chriſtian and a Drunkard! a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and a Swearer! a Chriſtian and a ſcoffer at godlineſs! I'le tel thee plainly, there are better Chriſtians in Hell a thouſandfold then thou art, if thou be'ſt ſuch an one. <hi>3dly,</hi> If thou art not a debauched perſon, then examine whether thou haſt any thing more then Civility and Morality; Thou doſt pride thy ſelf in thy civility, but O man or woman, where is thy faith, thy repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101421:27"/> thy holineſs? For to Hell thou muſt go with all thy ſweet diſpoſitions, and moral vertues, if theſe things be wanting. Thou maiſt be a moral man, and yet no Chriſtian; a civil, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred perſon, and yet in thy heart an enemy to Chriſt and the power of godlineſs.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt was on earth, he had not among the ſons of men a more malignant enemy then the civil honeſt Phariſees. And to this very day God's people do by experience find &amp; feel the moral civil man to be the moſt deſparate, indefatigable, inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and indefeaſable perſecutor they meet withal. The moral, civil men are the fitteſt Engines in the Devils work, and are able to do the moſt miſchief to God's people. Let a wicked drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, prophane fellow rail and ball againſt thoſe of his neighbors that do fear the Lord, or againſt any of Gods faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, calling them Hereticks and Phanatiques, &amp;c. there will hardly any take notice of ſuch a fellow, except it be to cry out ſhame upon him. But now in a Countrey-pariſh, where a good Miniſter is, it may be there you'l have a ſober, well-compoſed Gentleman, or ſome grave Yeoman that hath been an ancient Pariſhioner, and a loving, quiet neighbour, who hath compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many differences, and prevented many ſuits of Law among his neighbours (things very worthy of praiſe) And this man he deſigns the outing of this faithful Miniſter; and how doth he endeavour it? Not by railing againſt him to his face (though haply privately he may uſe as ſcurrilous language as others) but firſt he deals with the Miniſter himſelf, and tells him how ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he is that it ſhould be his fortune to come into ſuch a place where the people will by no means conform to his Rules; and therefore out of that love and reſpect he hath for him, he thought meet to adviſe him to remove, and to enquire out ſome other place where its likely he may have more love, and more maintenance If this wil do, he is pleaſed; but if he finds the Miniſter reſolved ſtill to wait upon the providence of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, then he deals with the Pariſhioners, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth them in this wiſe: Neighbours, you know how that for many years we lived in love and peace together, (as became us) &amp; good neighbourhood &amp; fellowſhip was maintained amongſt us, and how that we went comfortably to the Houſe of God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101421:28"/> together, and at the appointed ſeaſons had the Communion; and that our former Miniſters and we did live in love and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity one with another; but now ſince this Miniſter came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, it is nothing ſo; he doth ſeem by his preaching, to deſign the breaking of that former peace and union that was amongſt us: For, 1. He doth in his preaching preſs us to look after the truth of our converſion and regeneration, and after true ſaving faith; as if we were not converted, and had not true faith in God: And further, he uſually hath in his application a word for Saints, and a word for Sinners, as if there were two parties amongſt; whereas (neighbours) I hope, though we be great ſinners, yet we have all a ſtrong faith in Chriſt, and do love God (as God forbid we ſhould do otherwiſe) and rhat we are all true Chriſtians, let him ſay what he will. But <hi>2dly,</hi> we do already experience the ſad effects of his Miniſtry amongſt us in that ſome of our neighbors begin to cry out of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their ſin, and to queſtion the ſalvation of their ſouls, &amp;c. And beſides, in our Families there we are diſtracted, ſome of our Servants and Children they can mind nothing but read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and praying, and talking of the word they hear, &amp;c. So that the word is made good amongſt us; for here's the Father againſt the Son, and the Servant againſt his Maſter, and the Husband againſt his Wife, and ſo on, <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 34, 35, 36. And further, he doth refuſe to give us the Communion except we will give an account of our hope of ſalvation, and amend our lives. Now theſe things (neighbours) they are a trouble to me, and I ſuppoſe may be the like to many of you, to think that we who have been all along accounted good Neighbours, &amp; good Church-men, ſhould now in our elder years come to be cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed, and have our ſaith in God queſtioned. My advice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is (that this Gangreen may ſpread no further) that you would join as one man with me for the putting this Miniſter out, and getting an honeſt man that wil have charity for us all, and perform Church-duties, as others have done heretofore; and (as I am a Chriſtian) I ſhall be ſure to improve my Intereſt for the effecting it. But hear one word before I forget it; keep this Conference private, don'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let the Miniſter know that we had this meeting, or that I have thus adviſed you; for I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101421:28"/> (that I may the better accompliſh the thing intended) to carry it as fair to the Miniſter as I may; but do you be ſure to be true to the promiſe, and as I am a ſinner to God) I'le be true to mine. I ſay, that ſuch a man as this is, by ſuch means as theſe, ſhall be able to do more towards the extinguiſhing of a glorious light, the removing of a faithful Miniſter, the ruine of his family then a hundred prophane, drunken, idle fellows could have done; and indeed the prophane can do little, except headed, abetted, and encouraged by ſome ſuch perſons as theſe. Take heed therefore, left under the garb of Civility, thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineſt Enmity to Chriſt, and his People and Wayes. But then</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> Doſt thou boaſt not onely of thy Civility, but alſo of this, That thou art a Worſhipper of God; then examine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art not a Will-worſhipper; is not thy fear of God taught by the precepts of men? Art thou not carryed on in thy Worſhip more by the will of man, then by the wil of God? Art thou not more willing to take Humane, then Divine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in matters of Worſhip? The Word of God is the perfect Rule of Worſhip: Now what higher argument haſt thou for the greateſt part of thy Worſhip, then the Command and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of man? Thou art reſolved to be of the Religion of thy Countrey, be it what it will; and ſo it may well be judged, that if thou hadſt been born in <hi>India,</hi> or among the <hi>Turks,</hi> thou wouldſt have been of thy Countreys Religion, right or wrong. Undoubtedly one Act of Parliament (ſuppoſing all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants<note place="margin">Note.</note> of this Land were Papiſts) againſt the Papiſts, ſhould make more <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (in profeſſion) then a thouſand Sermons would do. Conſider, in matters of Worſhip art thou more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for thine own prayer, then for the wayes of Chriſt? More zealous for thee keeping of a holy-day, then for the keeping of the Lord's Day? More zealous of praying in thy Pew, then in thy Cloſet? More zealous for prayers over the dead, then for good, ſound, and powerful preaching? Nay, have not ſome of you been more troubled about the thoughts of your Burial, then you have about eternal proviſion for your precious ſouls? Thus the proud Phariſees were more zealous for the traditions of the Elders, then they were for the Commands of God. They
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101421:29"/> had an ancient Tradition among them for the Waſhing of hands before meat. And the Diſciples of Chriſt (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this was a very innocent Ceremony, yet) obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what weight the Jews laid upon it, and how they did impoſe it, denyed conformity, and were defended by Chriſt in it. But oh! how greatly were the Jews offended at their non-conformity? They themſelves could ſuffer the Law of God to be broken, had no zeal for God or his Commands, but for their own Traditions &amp; Commands they had great zeal, theſe muſt not be omitted by any means. And this is the very ſpirit of the man of Sin, and of all thoſe that do adhere unto him; for in the Romiſh Church you ſhall have them make more conſcience of a nod or a cringe, or a croſs, &amp;c. then of ſwearing, or whoring, or Sabbath-breaking, or any ſuch notorious wickedneſs; nay, it's more eaſie to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain pardon for any of theſe, then for non-conformity to any of their Eccleſiaſtical Laws.</p>
            <p>Search therefore whether thy Worſhip be not Will-Worſhip, whether thou art not ſuperſtitious in thy Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiping, doing what thou doeſt either without a command, or elſe without reſpect to the command of God, as thy chief and onely Rule in the matters of his Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Object.</hi> I am not able to diſcern between true and falſe Worſhip, and therefore I muſt truſt to the judgments of ſuch as I judge wiſer then my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The wiſeſt of men are ſubject to error, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt<note place="margin">Not to relye barely upon the judgments of men in matters Religion.</note> the beſt and ableſt there are great differences in matters of Worſhip. What ſort of men then canſt thou truſt? Unto what party then wilt thou cleave? Why, I'le cleave (it may be thou mayeſt anſwer) to that party that hath moſt power to impoſe their judgments upon me. I confeſs that's a good ſhift to keep thee from ſufferings; but if thou haſt no better, thou wilt hardly keep thy ſelf out of hell.</p>
            <p>2. At the great day of Chriſt, thou maiſt then anſwer for thy ſelf. There is none of thoſe upon whoſe ſleeves thou doeſt now pin thy faith, will then appear to plead for thee; it's well if they can plead their own cauſe. When God ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101421:29"/> ſay, <hi>Who required thoſe things at thy hand?</hi> it will not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for thee to anſwer, I had ſuch a mans command, and ſuch a mans judgment for it; for God will ſay, Did I ever require it? Thou ſhouldſt have made me, and not thy fellow-Creature the Lord of thy conſcience.</p>
            <p>3. It's a duty incumbent upon every of you to ſearch the Scriptures, <hi>Joh. 5. 39. Col.</hi> 3. 16. And it's the great work of a Miniſter of the Goſpel to endeavour ſo to enlighten his people, that in the performance of all religious duties they may walk by Scripture light, doing all in judgment. To be able, as the Apoſtle ſaith (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15) to pray and ſing with the ſpirit, and with underſtanding alſo.</p>
            <p>4. Without knowledg &amp; underſtanding in the wil of God, thy heart cannot be good, neither canſt thou be ſincere in thy Worſhip; minde that Scripture, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 9, 10, 11. neither canſt thou perform any duty that ſhall be well pleaſing in the ſight of God. See for that <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Finally, Art thou got a ſtep above all the former? Doſt thou not onely plead for a Worſhip, but a pure Worſhip, a Worſhip according to Scripture, a Virgin-Worſhip? Why then examine, Art thou not in the way of Hypocriſie? Is thy heart right with God? Is Chriſt thy all and in all? For know, that by ſo much the more glorious thy profeſſion is, and the greater thy light is, by ſo much the greater will thy condemnation be, if thy heart ſhall not be found to be right with God. And thus much for the firſt direction about Self-examination.</p>
            <p>Again <hi>ſecondly,</hi> In the handling of the ſecond Doctrine, we have opened thoſe terms whereby Chriſt offereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> now examine thy ſelf, whether thou haſt to this day cordially and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily received Chriſt upon thoſe terms? Received Chriſt, ſo as to deny and abhorr thy ſelf, ſo as to take up the Croſs, and ſo as to follow him, in his Commands, Examples, and Providences.</p>
            <p>3. And chiefly, if thou wouldeſt go thorow with this work, beg of God that he would pour forth of his ſpirit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thee; it being the great Office of this Spirit to diſcover <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> their own vileneſs, and Chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101421:30"/> their own ſinfulneſs, and Chriſts righteouſneſs; their own wants, and Chriſts fulneſs; their own guilt, and Chriſts ſatisfaction: The miſery of their eſtate, as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> and the happineſs of their eſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by virtue of union with the Lord Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> Joh. 16. 8, 9, 10, 11. 1 Cor. 2 9. to the end, Eph. 1. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. Be faithfull in the making uſe of theſe directions, and by the bleſſing of the Lord upon thee, thou mayeſt come to know the ſtate of thy ſoul, whether thou art in the broad way to deſtruction, or in the narrow ſtreight path to life and glory.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Uſe is of Exhortation, and that firſt<note place="margin">A Uſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> to thoſe who upon examination ſhall be found in the broad way that leadeth to ruine, ſhall be found walking in the path of Ignorance, Profaneſs, Diſobedience, Will-Worſhip, or Hypocriſie; them I exhort (being in ſome meaſure ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the terrours of the Almighty) with <hi>David</hi> to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their waies, and turn to the Lord, <hi>Pſal. 119. 59. I thought on my waies, and turned my feet unto thy teſtimonies.</hi> Conſider O Soul, what it is to be in this broad way; if thou knoweſt not, give me leave a little to acquaint thee: To be in this broad way (as all unregenerate perſons are) is to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world, without intereſt in him, or commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him; to be a ſtranger to the covenants of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to be without any true hope of Salvation: If thou knoweſt not, I'le tell thee; It's to be a filthy, loathſome, noiſome creature, more abominable to God then a Toad; to be an enemy of God, a childe of the Devil, in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and under the power of Darkneſs: If thou knoweſt not, I'le tell thee; It's to be a childe of wrath, and an heir of hell. This (and a thouſand-fold more then I can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs) is thy condition at preſent; and as for thy future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (if thou dyeſt unchanged) let it ſuffice that I tell thee thou ſhalt be damned, and puniſhed by an Almighty hand. All Gods works are like himſelf; if he loves a poor creature, he loves him like a God; if he hates a poor ſinner, it's the hatred of a God; if he ſaves a ſoul, he ſaves him like a God; and ſo if he damnes thy ſoul, and torments thee in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101421:30"/> hell, it will be the damnation and torment of a God. Hear this Sinners, and haſten out of this <hi>Sodom,</hi> before God rains down fire and brimſtone upon you. Ariſe, depart, for this is not your reſt, it's polluted, and take Chriſts counſel, <hi>Strive to enter in at this ſtreight gate,</hi> to walk in this narrow path whatever it coſt thee; and that this may ſtick, minde theſe two arguments:</p>
            <p n="1">1. There's no life but in this narrow way; all that ever went to heaven went through this ſtrait gate; there's no ſalvation without Chriſt, and no Chriſt without belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and no believing without holineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ere long, Striving time will be over; Life and Death are now offered to your choice; you are now told, <hi>If that yee live after the fleſh, ye ſhall dye; but if ye through the ſpirit mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 13.</note> 
               <hi>the deeds of the fleſh, ye ſhall live.</hi> You have as yet a <hi>may be</hi> for ſalvation, which if you neglect, you will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be damned. This is the day of Chriſts patience, the golden Scepter is yet held forth, Mercy is yet upon the bare knee to poor ſinners, but when once the Maſter of<note place="margin">Luke 13. 25.</note> the houſe be riſen up and hath ſhut to the door, then ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving will be in vain. It will then be in vain to ſay ye were baptized in his Name, and that you have eat and drank at his Table; Chriſt will then ſay, Depart ye workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, I know you not: What! you baptized in my Name, you eat and drink in my preſence? What! and blaſpheme my Name, and contemn my people, and profane my Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and ſwear, and be drunk, &amp;c. Away ſaith Chriſt, depart, I know not whence you are: ſince you would not in the day of my Patience give me entertainment into your heart, neither will I now entertain you in my glory. Then will be fulfilled that, Revel. 22. 11. <hi>He that is unjuſt let him be unjuſt still, and he that is filthy let him be filthy ſtill, &amp;c.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this time preaching will ceaſe, and the ſtrivings of the bleſſed Spirit will ceaſe, and all hopes of ſalvation will ceaſe for ever. Oh! therefore ſtrike while the Iron is hot, while Grace is profered accept i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, while the Spirit ſtrives with thee yield unto him; ſuffer thy ſelf to be overcome by the Spirit in a way of Mercy, or elſe God will overcome thee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101421:31"/> in a way of Wrath and Indignation. The concernment of the ſoul is made a by-buſineſs with the moſt in the world, and is taken care for in the laſt place. Moſt do by their ſouls, as it hath been formerly ſaid of the Courtiers, that they do all things late; riſe late, and dine late, and go to bed late, and (that which is worſt of all) they uſually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent late. It was my obſervation in the Countrey, that it was rare to have prayers deſired for the Sick, or any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel deſired from the Miniſter to the Sick, till all hopes of life was even gone: So that (generally) if publick prayers were deſired, or the Miniſter ſent for, you might conclude nothing but death was expected. Take heed of thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring repentance; for conſider, that though true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be never too late, yet late repentance is ſeldom true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt ſaved one at the laſt hour (as the Thief upon the Croſs) that none might deſpair, and it was but one that ſo none might preſume.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider that the day of Grace may be over with<note place="margin">Note.</note> thee before thy life is ended. God doth often in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment give men up to hardneſs of heart, and blindeneſs of minde, <hi>that in ſeeing they might ſee and not perceive, and in hearing they might hear and not underſtand, &amp;c.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that perſons have withſtood a powerfull Miniſtry, it may be ten, twenty, thirty, or fourty yeares, and in this time the Spirit hath ſtrove with them, and perſwaded them (times without number) to cloſe with Chriſt, and forſake ſin, and could never prevail upon them, then doth God ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially give them up to their own hearts luſts, commands his Spirit to ſtrive no more with them, and giveth a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Devil to take them for his own, and to ſeal them up unto the day of wrath. Conſider a little what a dreadfull Judgment this is; for firſt it is a ſpiritual Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now the ſpirituality of this Judgment conſiſts in theſe three particulars: 1. In that it is upon the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al part of man, it is to have the heart fatned, the minde blinded, the conſcience ſeared, &amp;c. <hi>Iſai. 6. 9, 10. Math. 13. 14 15. Mark 4. 12. John 12. 40. Acts 18. 26, 27. Rom. 11. 8. 1 Tim.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. 2. In that it is executed by a Spirit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101421:31"/> and commiſſioned for that work, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3, 4. It is the great work of Satan to harden and blind the hearts of ſuch as do ſlight and oppoſe Chriſt. <hi>3dly,</hi> In that it is with reſpect to ſpiritual bleſſings, leſt they ſhould ſee, and underſtand, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel ſhould ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and they ſhould be converted, and healed. This judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is to this end, that thoſe who before would not ſee, now may not ſee; that thoſe who before oppoſed and ſhut out the light, may now for ever be rendered uncapable of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goſpel-Myſteries; that the light of the glorious Goſpel may never break in upon their hearts. So that a ſoul under this judgement is not capable of receiving any benefit by the means of Grace, be it never ſo powerful and glorious: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſaith not (<hi>Luke 19. 42.) but now they are taken from thine eyes,</hi> (for at this time they had Chriſt's Miniſtry among them, and afterwards the Miniſtry of the Apoſtles) but ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Now they are hid from thine eyes:</hi> So that perſons judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially hardened, are under the power of ſuch darkneſs, that though the Goſpel be preacht to them, yet it's hid from them, and becomes not the ſavour of life to life, but the ſavour of death to death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> This Judgement is irrevocable. The ſoul is loſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; it's impoſſible to renew him unto Repentance; there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains now no more ſacrifice for ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 6. &amp; 10. 26, 27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> To compleat the dread of this Judgement, conſider that the ſoul is here ſtruck inſenſibly; mortally wounded, and knows it not. This we may ſee in <hi>Eſau,</hi> who though he was much tormented that his brother <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould circumvent him, yet could find no place for repentance, no place wherein to change his mind, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 17. The man had the plague at his heart, was given up to a reprobate ſence; but this he knows not, he bewails not: We feel the ſmart of outward Judgments, and they often do us good; but this giveth a deadly wound, and is not felt: This ſtroke makes perſons that before would melt under a Sermon, and be moved by counſel and reproof, to be Sermon and Counſel-proof, make them able to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt all Aſſaults that ſhall be made againſt them. If this be ſo, then it concerns you to make out after Chriſt while there
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101421:32"/> are any movings and ſtirrings upon your ſpirit, left you be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to this dreadful Judgement. There are three bad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions upon a dying bed; 1. Good counſel refuſed. 2. Vows and Promiſes not performed. And, 3. Strong Conviction rejected, and not obeyed. Thus much by way of Argument:</p>
            <p>Object. It's poſſible ſome may here object<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>That it's in vain for them to ſeek, ſince Chriſt ſaith,</hi> (Luke 13. 24.) <hi>That many of thoſe that ſeek, ſhall not be able to enter in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The great reaſon why the moſt wil fall ſhort, is becauſe they can't ſubmit to the terms afore-mentioned, they can't with that Merchant (<hi>Matt.</hi> 13. 46.) part with all for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the Pearl.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What then may I do to bring my heart to ſubmit to thoſe terms?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Study the worth and excellency of thy precious and immortal Spirit. It would be but a bad bargain, though thou ſhouldſt gain the whole world, if thou ſhouldſt loſe thy ſoul, <hi>Job<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 27, 8. Mark</hi> 8. 36, 37. This well ſtudyed, would ſoon make thee willing to deny all, to forſake all, ſo thou might'ſt ſave thy ſoul <hi>2dly,</hi> Conſider, that the deſign of the Devil and ſin, is to undo thee for ever; for Luſt when it is conceived, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth ſin; and ſin when it is perfected, will moſt certainly bring forth death, <hi>Jam. 1. 15. 3dly,</hi> And chiefly, Study the worth and excellency of Chriſt; What ever thou denieſt for Chriſt, thou wilt find it abundantly made up in him; If Riches, <hi>durable Riches are with him,</hi> Prov. 8. 18. If Honor, All that believe in him are made Sons and Heirs, and that of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Joh. 1. 12 <hi>Rom. 8. 15, 16, 17. Gal. 3. 26. Joh.</hi> 17. 22. If Pleaſures, <hi>At his right hand are pleaſures for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16. ult. If the rags of thine own righteouſnes, he wil become <hi>the Lord thy Righteouſneſs;</hi> Jer. 23. 6. If thine own wiſdom, <hi>In him are hid the treaſures of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge,</hi> Col. 2. 3. Hadſt thou but a ſight of Chriſts glory, a taſt of his goodneſs, thou wouldſt be willing to part with all other things, ſo thou mighteſt but enjoy him.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:101421:32"/>
            <p>My laſt word is to ſuch as have engaged in Heavens way, in the ſtrait path; My Exhortation to you is, that you would hold on your way, and perſevere unto the end. Though your trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhould be great, and your Friends few, yet know that you are in a bleſſed path, and that your end will be peace. Let not therefore vain Worldlings baffle you out of your Religion; let neither the frowns for ſmiles of men cauſe you to decline the wayes of God, and walk in any accurſed path. I'le propoſe two Scriptures for your conſideration, and ſo conclude; one is <hi>Heb. 10. 38. Now the Juſt ſhall live by faith</hi> (and hee'l make a good living on it) <hi>but if any man draw back, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</hi> The other is <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 38. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 10 32, 33. and <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 8, 9. where our Lord ſaith, <hi>That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall confeſs him before men, him will he confeſs before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his holy Angels; but whoſoever ſhall deny him</hi> (be the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration wherein he liveth, never ſo adulterous and wicked, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo full of malignity and cruelty) <hi>him will he deny when he ſhall come in his own glory, and in the glory of his Father, and in the glory of his holy Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good Lord cauſe the rain of his bleſſing to fall upon theſe Lines, <hi>Amen,</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
